Welcome back, everybody.
Last few lectures we talked extensively
about two of these four fundamental
effects of programming.
namely Try and Future.
But maybe you got the feeling that,
you know, we pulled Try and
Future a little bit out of the hat
like a rabbit, like a magician.
All right?
And what I'm going to do now is I'm
going to show you that actually try and
future are closely related and that you
know you can derive one from the other.
And then we're going to use that
same trick on the other side where
we will take interable and
use this same trick to get observable.
And what is this trick?
[SOUND] Well, in order to do the trick
we need to break down
futures into their essence.
Okay?
So here is the type of Future and,
just to remind you,
Future has a on complete method.
What we did before is we got, used unit
here instead of u, for simplicity.
But it takes a callback that takes
a function from try to unit, and
then return unit.
[SOUND] All right, so
if we simplify this all away, so
we remove the trait, because this is
a trait with just a single function.
Then, [SOUND] what we're left with
is this higher order function.
So it's a Try of T to unit.
Two units, all right?
So all I've done is just
removed the trait and
turned that method in the trait
into a standalone function.
[SOUND] Now,
the next thing we're going to do is,
we're going to reverse all the arrows.
So we're going to reverse all the arrows,
so, try to units,
to units, becomes, unit arrow,
unit arrow Try of T.
Now this is a kind of a little bit
weird thing in Scala when you know,
when you return here, unit You might
also say that's going to, you know?
That we are going to tank, change that on
the left hand side into the empty tuple.
Because there's no value of that unit
that you can pass as a parameter.
Okay?
So we're kind of, you know,
cleaning this up a little bit.
And then, remember, that what we said.
Is that a future only [SOUND]
produces a single value.
So, every time you call the future
it will just return the same value
whenever you put in a new call back.
So those unit arrows in
front of the Try of T
really do nothing because there
there cannot be any side effects.
Because you're always
getting the same value.
So if we simplify that,
then we get Try of T.
So the magic here, is that we started
with this simple version of future.
We reversed the arrows.
We simplified, and we got Try of T.
And this trick of flipping
the arrows is called duality.
And here you see the duality in
a slightly more intuitive form.
If you look at a function
[SOUND] of Type future of T.
What is that?
It's a function that
receives a result of type.
Type Try of T they are call back.
All right.
And so
it's like asynchronous receives that.
And a function that returns
a Try of T directly
blocks until the method's returned.
So the duality here is between
synchronous and asynchronous and
the way we implement that is by kind
of blocking or passing a callback.
[SOUND] Now if you go to Wikipedia.
And you search for duality, you get,
like a, whole definition of duality.
But the essence there is that
you're flipping the arrows.
[SOUND] And since this is not a full
course on category theory I will
kind of leave it here, but
the thing is that when you use duality,
it's like buy one get one free.
And I'm Dutch, you know, you probably
heard that from my accent, and
Dutch people are cheap and we like,
really like buy one get one free.
So that's the reason I,
I, I'm so attracted.
To this notion of duality.
[SOUND] All right, so that was our short
derivation to go from Try to Future.
And now we will go and,
do intervals, and then at some point
we'll use the same trick to
dualize intervals to observables.
So see you next time.