Welcome back everybody.
Last time,
I explained very quickly a magic trick
that we could use to
turn futures into try.
Or, you know, you could,
we could have started with, try as well,
and convert that to futures.
What we're going to do now is we're
going to use that same dualization trick
on the right hand side of our,
square of effect.
And we're going to use that to
turn iterables into observables,
so that's the thing here on the right.
Let's recall what, iterables are.
Iterables are a pair of traits.
The first trait is iterable that has
a factory function to create iterator.
So that's the function iterator.
Which returns an iterator.
And then once we get an iterator,
you can call has next
which returns a boolean indicating
if this iterator has more elements.
And when has next tells you true, you will
call next to give you the next value.
All right?
So it's a pair of traits
that represent collections.
And you see here, in this case,
because you co-maxed,
these are pull based collections.
You're pulling every time for
the next element.
And, to go back to our little game,
imagine that we have a list of coins.
A list is a kind of iterable, so
there we have our iterable of coins.
And once we want to pull all
the coins out of our wallet,
we have to first get the iterator.
And then we go typically in
a loop while there are more
values in the iterator we call next.
And that's the way we collect our coins.
Now notice that this is
a synchronous stream or
a pull based stream every time we connect
we block until the next value is produced.
And, we'll see the consequences that,
of that later.
But of course, the first thing we should
note is that iterable is a monad.
And why is it a monad?
Because it has flatMap, and
it has a constructor to take a single
value and inject it into an iterable.
And of course, just having flatMap and
a constructor's not that interesting.
And, iterable support all
the methods that we know and love.
Like filter, map, and
then there's the domain specific ones.
Such as stake,
which takes the first N element.
Or takeWhile, It takes a boolean,
and iterates over the iterable,
and, you know, copying the values
as long as that predicate is true.
And then last but not least,
there's our friend, zip.
Now, the nice thing here is that iterable,
since it's an interface,
now there's many concrete
types that implement iterable.
Okay, so many many concrete
And we can forget about all
these concrete types and
just think of iterable as a collection,
okay.
So any type that implements
iterable is a collection and
we can draw that collection.
As a picture like this
where we have a line and
then there's the subsequent element.
And map takes a function and,
in this case a function that turns,
marbles into diamonds.
And applies that function to
every element of the list.
And the beauty of interface based
programming is that it doesn't matter what
the underlying collection is,
and in fact, very important.
There might not even be an underlying
collection because this iterator
will produce the next value on the map.
So this is the beauty.
There might never be an underlying
collection like a list or an array.
You could just create them on the fly.
Now let me remind you of the typical
execution times of a PC on a human scale.
Remember sending packets took a long time.
Reading from memory took a long time.
And what we're going to do now,
is we're going to use iterables
to read stuff from memory.
So here's the example.
Read lines from this, takes a path,
and returns, an, iterator of strength.
And this is just a standard SCALA code,
and, and then we're going to do a for
loop to get, do work for each line.
Now reading from disk takes two weeks,
so two weeks per line.
That's kind of crazy because
we're blocking again.
We're waiting for a long time,
so reading from a file using
iterators is not a good idea.
Because the latency is not the,
this is not the type.
To deal with things
that have high latency.
So what we want to do is we want
to use our magical dualization
trick to take this type of iterables
that are synchronous streams.
And turn it into a type that
represents asynchronous streams, so
things that have high latency.
Just like we went from try of t,
to future of t.
We're going to go from iterable
of t to a new type and
that's observable of t, all right.
So the first thing we're going to
do is we're going to simplify.
If you look at the iterator type here,
this has next, has no business there.
We can simulate this by having
next return an option of T and
if has next returns false,
the option is empty or nothing.
And if it's if it does return a value,
then it's just T, okay?
So we can take these two methods and
turn them into one.
Now, whenever we see a trait
that has a single method,
we can turn that just
into a type declaration.
There's no need to have a,
a complete trait.
It's just, you know?
This thing is just a function
from unit to option of t.
So let's just define that as just
a function from unit to option of T.
Now we can substitute that function,
that type, because,
you know, if it's just a single function,
let's substitute it there an iterator.
And now we have a trait that also has
a single method, so just let expand that.
And now we get a type iterable
that's really a type unit
arrow unit arrow try of t.
All right.
So, what we have done is we just
simply fight the trait iterable and
iterator and the essence is just
this higher order function.
Okay?
I've done nothing special.
Okay.
So, given these two things,
we have simplified it into
something that only has arrows.
And the reason I wanted to simplify
this way is I'm going to use the magic
trick of dualization.
And that means I have
to reverse the arrows.
And now I have my type in
a shape that only has arrows.
So here we go.
Iterable unit arrow unit
arrow try option of t.
And now we're going to go and
switch the arrows around.
See you after the break.