Hi there,
we just finished simplifying the two
threads interval into one
type that only has arrows,
and the reason we did that is
that we wanted to used our
magic dualization trick to
reverse the arrows, and
that requires us to have a type that
is just expressed in terms of arrows.
So here's our type iterable.
It's a factory of factories
of values where the values can
either be a single value or
nothing, or the whole creation
of the value might fail.
And I love this type.
I mean, this type,
there's no noise of traits or anything.
It's just the essence
of what an iterable is.
It's a factory of factories, and
that's also beautiful by itself.
But we're not going to talk
about iterables anymore.
We're going to talk about
the dual of iterables.
Namely a push based type
where we can get sequences of
values in an asynchronous way
because here you see that here the,
here you can see the synchrony.
Right?
I have a function from unit to try of T,
and
that function is going to block
until the next value arrives.
So let's turn the arrows around,
flip the arrows around, and there we go.
We just flipped the arrows around.
And what we're going to do now is we're
going to do the dual of simplification
which is complexification, so
we're going to take this type here and
we're going to complexify it.
I'm not going to try to understand
what it means right now.
The first thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to complexify this type.
And complexify means that just
when we remove traits and
turn them into functions we're going
to now turn functions back into traits.
All right?
So that's what I mean by complification.
So the first thing is to
give this guy a name.
And let's call this type observable of T.
Fo, observable f,
t is a setter of a setter, like this.
Okay.
Now, the first thing we're
going to do is now look
at what part of this we can
turn into its own thing.
And the first thing we're
going to do here is to look at
this ugly try of option of t.
And, you know, as I said, it,
it requires better matching, and
all the complexity, and in the end,
the way you look at a function that does
pattern matching on a value of try of
option of T, it will have three cases.
The try case, so that's,
you get a throwable.
If it's not a throwable then there's
two cases when there's nothing or
where there's just a value.
All right?
So when we pattern match over
a function that has an argument
drive object of T really we get three
cases, and those are the function.
So we just split this into
these three functions.
So instead of tryOption of T to unit,
we get three functions.
Now we see three functions, so
what are we going to do with that?
Well, we're going to put those into its
own type, and then substitute it in there.
So what is an observable now?
It's a function from observer to unit.
And an observer is a triple of functions.
Good, so
now we have split the rope there and
now we're going to continue to
complexify because instead of
having a triple of functions we're
going to put those in a trait.
Then what we're going to do at the same
time is we're going to turn these
functions Into definitions.
All right.
So this triple of three functions becomes
one trade with three methods,
onError, onCompleted and onNext.
And nothing here changes, right?
So the observable still
takes an observer to unit.
But I just want to leave this here to
remind you that these three functions
are now represented by that single trait.
Okay, continue complexification.
What we're going to do now is we're
going to turn this observable Into it's
rate as well, by introducing a method,
and let's call that method subscribe,
and that then takes an observer and
returns unit, okay?
So, all we have done is we have
kind of split this complicated
entry of option of T arrow
unit into this trait.
And then we have introduced a trait for
observable as well that takes an observer.
It's all straightforward,
these things are all equal.
So here is our type after dualization.
And now it's time to
interpret what this means.
Well, And
observable is something that I can feed
a go back and
that go back consists of three functions.
What happens when there's a regular value?
And the difference with futures is that
this go back can be called many times,
zero or more.
And then the, so it represents a stream.
And then the stream can either complete
normally or complete with an error.
All right?
So really it's, it's a little bit like
in Java where you have a button and
a button has different call backs for
clicks and mouseover and whatever.
So the same here.
There's an observable that
takes a a trait that has
callbacks for
various different events that can happen.
And, delivery of a value,
the end of a stream or an exception.
Now the truth is a little
bit more complicated,
because just like with a button where,
where you have an event,
you add an event handler or a call back,
you might want to remove the call back.
All right?
And what we do here is we
have that when you subscribe
to an observable, with an observer,
what you get back is a subscription.
And a subscription is this thread
that allows you to unsubscribe.
It means,
remove this observer from this observable.
And, when you know JavaScript or
any language that uses events or
call backs like C# or
as I said, JavaScript.
You have the same mechanism you can
add an event and earn and do it,
and then you can remove it.
And in this case we remove it is
by returning a special object with
a matter to remove it, and
then you have a bouillon here as well that
you can check whether the,
the call back has been removed.
All right, so
let's put them side by side, and
now you see here, observable,
it has this notion of subscription.
The onNext, onError, and
onCompleted are really, kind of,
you know, encoding of these two methods
plus the fact that this can throw.
And then you see here that
the iterable and iterate.
I'm sorry, the iterable and
the observable are similar
except that one returns an iterator and
the other one takes an observer.
Now, in .NET and in other languages
the iterators,
also have a notion of subscription.
Because if you're iterating over
a collection, the consumer might want to
tell the producer I'm not
interested in any more values.
And in that case it can be
that the iterable iterator,
traits also have a notion of subscription.
But in Scholar and
in Java that's not the case.
But if you look in Dart or
C# there is the case.
All right, so
now we have seen all four effects.
We started out with Try of T to make
clear that computation could fail.
Then we moved on to futures.
Riches and monads that an effect,
that tells you that a computation
takes time, and can fail.
We show that these two were
connected via duralization.
Then we looked at synchronous collections.
So collections, of values where you pull,
where you block.
Just like, you know, when you have
a function here that you block.
And then we use the same dualization
trick to go from here to here.
All right.
Thank you so much.
Now we know how all these
four effects are deeply
connected via the magic
of category theory.
Thank you so much and see you next time.