Hey everybody, welcome back.
I must say I'm a little bit
tired of all this theory and
duality and functions and so on.
Let's write some code.
And in particular let's write some, kind
of, simple examples using observables.
In the jam sessions we will
show some bigger demos.
But here I just want to show you
the basics of using observables
you know, in a real program.
And the program we're going to
show here is the following.
We're first going to generate
an observable streams
that will fire a value every one second.
And something like a clock or
some temporal stream like that is
the ultimate example of
an asynchronous stream.
You're not going to ask every
second give me the next value.
No, every second a new value will
be delivered to you automatically.
Whether you want it or not.
It's a little bit like
the old fashioned newspaper.
Every morning it just shows
up on your door step,
assuming that you're still
reading a paper newspaper.
And it's just kind of,
you know, coming at you.
And then at some point when
you don't want it anymore,
you unsubscribe from the newspaper,
and the same here.
When you're finished
listening to this stream,
finishing getting something every so
often, you just unsubscribe from it.
But since observables are collections we.
We have all the operators available
over collections just like interval.
So for example we can filter them.
And in this case here, you see that we're
filtering out all the ticks that are even.
And then the next thing we're going to do,
is we're going to group these
tics together in chunks of two,
shifted by one.
And for that, we have the operator sliding
buffer, that takes two parameters,
the count, so that's the length of
our buffer, and then how far to skip.
And we're going to subscribe to
the result of buffering that stream
in two chunks of two shifted by one.
And by just doing a print line and
then, you know,
we do a read line in between there and
then we unsubscribe.
Now read line is deprecated so
I will, don't dare to show it.
On the slides, but I will, I'm using
it anyway because it's convenient.
Okay, when we run this code we will
see that the it will print zero two.
So it has first filtered out one and
then it groups these in two.
And then we get two four,
four six, et cetera.
So here you see how this program works.
Now I mentioned a couple of times, when
you're dealing with these collections, and
especially when you're dealing with Rx
collections, observable collections,
it's really good idea to
draw these marble diagrams.
And a marble diagram is a diagram
where time goes from left to right.
So you see there the arrow of time.
And then there's marbles on that line
that denote the values that appear
at a certain point in time.
So if we look at the marble diagram for
ticks, it will have zero, one,
two, et cetera.
With the spacing in between there and
being one second.
Now, notice that what one second
means is completely abstract,
in particular,
Rx has the notion of virtual time.
And in this case, one second
corresponds to one second on the,
the world clock time, but
it doesn't have to be like that at all.
Now the next thing is we're going to
filter out all the text that are even,
now we just use the regular filter,
passing it a predicate.
And that will drop out all
the odd numbers from the stream.
And then finally where we're
using this sliding buffer and
there you see we're kind of taking
chunks of two shifted by one.
And there is the output.
So this, you know, I, I really recommend
whenever you're stuck even with intervals
but especially with observables,
draw these marble diagrams.
They will be tremendously helpful.
And let's finish off by showing how this
looks in the IDE, here I'm using IntelliJ.
Here you see our main program.
There's sticks, evens buffers
I'm subscribing here, you see.
Read line.
Promised you I still use it, even though
it's deprecated so it's crossed out.
And then I unsubscribed.
So in this case, I run this code and
what happens is that you know,
it prints out two zero two two four,
et cetera.
Then I hit Return and
then the stream gets unsubscribed and
then I don't get any new values.
Hey, the other interesting thing here.
Is that if you look here.
You see all the types
that are available in Rx.
And in the next few lectures we
will discuss, discuss many of them.
But we won't have time
to discuss all of them.
But, you know,
you can see them right there.
And as I said,
in the jam sessions we will show you some
cool examples of simple games and
so on all using Rx.
But remember,
nothing beats writing codes yourself.
So, really, you know, whenever you're
trying to solve one of the solutions or
you're trying to follow the codes,
just type it in your favorite IDE and
play around with it,
such that you get a better understanding.
Thank you so much, and see you next week.