Hi, everybody.
Welcome back to the lecture
series on reactive extensions and
this time, we're going to look
at a few of the Rx Operators.
And since observable and
observer form a monet
we have all the usual high order
functions that we have seen for
tried and we have seen for
iterable and that we have seen for
future and they are here also for
observable of T.
And flatMap, map, filter take and so on.
And in this case, you see that
all the operators are the same,
the domain-specific ones
are the same as for iterables,
because observables are collections.
Here to remind you is
the marble diagram for map.
Map takes a input stream.
In this case, an input stream of marbles
and turns each marble into a diamond.
And as you see here, doesn't really
matter what the stream represents.
That's the beauty of
these marble diagrams.
This could be an iterable or
an observable.
But, you know,
the map function behaves the same.
Here is a marble diagram for a flatMap.
A flatMap for observables is certainly
different than flatMap for iterables.
And the reason is that observable
streams are asynchronous,
which means that the function
that you're flat mapping over
your input stream will produce
its values asynchronously.
Now when you have an iterable,
what happens when you flatMap is that you
take the,
you pull the first value out of the input,
you apply it to the flatMap function
to the function you pass into flatMap.
You get another stream and
that get pulled, you know, out.
And when that's finishes and
you pull for the next value,
you pull for the next value in
the in the outer input sequence.
But with observables you're not pulling
the sequences themselves
push values at you.
So the implem,
implementation has to be different.
And in this case, what happens
is that every time a new value
arrives on the input stream,
the function is called and
that one will produce
the values asynchronously and
all the results will be merged
into the output stream.
And if you look at this
example here say that every,
that the flatMap function takes a diamond.
Sorry, a, a, a marble and
turns that into a,
a diamond and a square of the same color.
And what you see here is that
the output gets merged together, but
the order of the individual
streams is maintained.
So you see, for
example there the green diamond comes
before the green square and
that's always the case.
So, if you look at the definition
of map in observable,
it's really defined as
a map followed by a merge.
Here's another example that explains how
nested streams are merged and
let's look at that.
So what we start with a simple stream
that has the values three, two, one.
Then what we do is we
create an interval of the,
the, the length of the, of the number.
So the first one, number three will send
out the value three at each three seconds.
And then the second stream
will send out the value two,
the green thing there, every two seconds.
And then finally the blue one will
be sent out every one second.
And when you run this program and
the code, by the way,
will be available at the GitHub site.
You will see that the output get merged.
And that even though the green three was
the first value in the input stream exist,
it comes out after both the one and
the first to have been emitted.
All right.
So this is merge as I said.
It just takes two streams
asynchronous streams and
whenever a value appears,
it will be copied on the.
Some sense And nonderdim,
nondeterministic merge of two streams.
Now you can also use concat, that,
that's more like how it works for
iterables on observables, but
this is a little bit dangerous.
So, let's look at why it's dangerous
by taking the same example and
instead of merge,
we're using concate, over here.
Okay?
So,
instead of merging the resulting streams,
we concatenate them.
And concatenation means
the same as concatenation.
In iterables,
you wait until the stream terminates and
then you concatenate the other stream,
the second stream to the first stream.
And in this case,
what that means is that you have to be,
we start with the red three,
which is emitted each three seconds.
We can only start admitting the twos and
ones after, you know, we have
admitted the two threes and we can admit
the ones after we admitted the two twos.
Showing this comcat as
the buffer internally and
that makes comcats not streaming.
Okay?
So that's why you know you probably should
never use comcat observable streams.
Because it has to kind of, you know,
remember the second stream until
the first stream has terminated in
order to, to concatenate it at the end.
Here's the picture of concatenate and
where you see this behavior very
clearly the yellow marble there,
comes before the last blue
marble in the first stream.
But we have to delay it when
we concatenate it here,
because it has to come after
the blue marble of the first stream.
And so this is a dangerous and
expensive operation.
Okay.
Now, let's look at the,
a little bit more practical example.
Where we're taking earthquakes.
Earthquakes are the ideal example
of a asynchronous data stream.
Because, you know,
they get pushed at you and
there's no way you can kind of
stop them or, or whatever.
They just come whenever they want to.
And what we do here is we have
a little wrapper that uses
squares retrofit to wrap the US
geological service earthquake service.
And here is the kind of code.
Again, it will be available on GitHub.
And what we're going to do now is we're
going to do some simple queries over
earthquake streams.
So the first thing that we want to do
is we want to find out the location and
the magnitude of all major earthquakes.
So, in the previous example you saw
that we had an enumeration that mapped
the the number that you get from
the geological earthquake thing into
a magnitude.
And here is what we do is we, we get our
observable earthquakes, then we map.
And what we do is we
pick out the location and
we grid a magnitude from this
double into a magnitude value and
then we filter out all the major
earthquakes and then we just print them.
Okay?
So, it's very, very simple.
We, we map and
filter over these asynchronous streams.
Now, imagine that we have another
service the reverse GeoCode.
Where given the GeoCoordinates,
or lat, long, or
some other GeoCoordinate and what we want
to get back is a future of countries.
And again, here we're using a future,
because when you GeoCode,
you get one results.
So we encode that using a future and
this example here shows how futures and
observables can work together.
So, in this case, what we're going to
do is we're going to start with our
earthquake stream and
then we map over that.
For each quake, we get a future
that represents the location.
And then what we do is
we convert that future
into an observable using the helper
function observable from.
So, observable from takes a future and
turns it into an observable.
And then what we can do is we get
an observable of observables,
because we do the map and all the flatMap.
And then we have a choice whether we
flatten the stream or comcat it or
merge flatten and
merge are synonyms or we comcat them.
So here's what happens when
we flatten the streams.
In this case,
the earthquakes get out of sync.
So, the red earthquake, the GeoCode
process might take a long time.
Second earthquake comes in.
There, the GeoCode intakes a little time.
And what we see is then,
that the, in the output now that
the second earthquake comes
before the first earthquake.
And if you want to maintain
the temporal order of the earthquakes,
this is not a good situation.
So, in that case,
we will have to use comcat in order to
make sure that the earthquakes
remain in the right order.
Now, as I said this is
a little bit dangerous,.
But in this case,
since the future only returns one value,
you only have to ever kind of
buffer a couple of values and
assuming that things are not too slow,
this should work.
But in general,
you might have to kind of, you know,
use some form of time out to
avoid infinite buffering.
All right.
The last operator we're
going to show is groupBy.
So now that we have reverse
GeoCoded our earthquakes from
GPS locations into countries, we now want
to group the earthquakes by country.
And let's start with
the merge earthquakes.
And here you see, it's really simple.
We just say,
group the earthquakes by country and
what we now get is a stream that have,
as have a key a stream of streams
with a key being the country and
then a stream of the country And
the earthquake.
So you can do all the operations that
you do on the regular collections on
observable collections.
So thank you so much.
This was the end of the Rx Operators and
see you after the break.