Hey, welcome back.
One of the topics that we
didn't really drill in,
we mentioned it in passing kind of,
you know, is the idea of subscriptions.
When we derive observables and
observer from iterable iterator,
we mentioned that in observable for
operational reasons,
we wanted to be able to remove
the observer from an observable when,
you know, the consumer was not interested
anymore in receiving more values.
In this lecture, we're going to kind
of drill in a little bit
into the subscription type.
Here's example of earthquakes.
So we have a stream of earthquakes and
we subscribe to this twice.
Okay?
So then we get back to subscriptions,
as one and as zero.
And the important thing here is
that when we unsubscribe as one,
so we remove the first observer here,
that s2 will keep receiving
earthquake notifications.
But s1 or observer one, I should say,
will not receive anymore.
Okay?
Now sometimes, we but
when we say, subscription and,
you know, unsubscribe,
we mean cancel or we say, cancel.
But that's not really the case, right?
Because both, the, the other one
keeps receiving notifications.
Now, you know,
together with this notion of subscription
comes the idea of hot
versus cold observables.
And this idea is also present for
iterables,
but maybe it's not so
apparent as with observables,
but it, it happens there as well.
So what is a cold observable?
Well, a cold observable is when
you subscribe to an observer,
you get your own private
copy of the string.
So, in this case, because the way we
implemented the code using retrofit.
Whenever we subscribe to the earthquake's
stream, they're creating
a separate connection to the US Geological
Server Service and you will kind
of keep receiving your own values and
that's called a cold observable.
Another example of a cold observable
is say that you want to create
a stream of random numbers.
Now, every time you
subscribe to that stream,
you want to get your own
copy of random numbers.
You don't want to share the random numbers
between the different subscribers.
So, one way to look at the cold
observable is as an observable,
where the subscription
causes a side effect.
So you subscribe to a stream,
you get back a subscription and
that function call will
have a side effect.
And that subscription kind of represents
your own private copy of the stream.
A hot observable is slightly different and
there,
you often think about a UI event,
for example.
If you look at mouse moves,
the mouse is moving no matter what.
So, if you subscribe to mouse moves,
you're all kind of listening
to the same underlying stream.
And there one way to look at that,
it's that subscribing to that
stream has no effect, because you're
not getting your private copy.
So your subscription is
all shared together.
In the jam sessions,
we will show some concrete examples of
this where you can see the difference.
But for now think of simple, you know,
when you subscribe to an observable that
subscribe action can have a side effect.
In which case, we call it hot or
it can have no side effect.
Sorry, in that case, we have it cold.
When it does not have a side effect,
we call it hot.
All right.
So as I said, we often confuse the word
cancellation and unsubscribing.
But in general, when you have two
subscriptions to one observable and
one of the subscriptions is unsubscribed
it has no influence on the other.
So you're not cancelling
the underlining computation and
also, you know you,
you it depends on the stream.
If the stream is hot, you don't want
to,even if there's no subscribers,
you might not want to kill
the underlying computation.
Because later,
a new subscriber might come in and
then you want to kind of
catch on where you were.
You don't want to kind of introduce yet,
another side effect.
So these are all subtle issues
when you are implementing your own
observables to keep in mind.
But again, there's no difference if you
create your own iterables by implementing
iterable and iterator directly, you have
to think about all these issues as well.
Okay.
Let's now zoom in into
our subscription type.
So subscription has two methods.
It's unsubscribe that you can check
whether the subscription has been
unsubscribed and then there's a side
effecting function here, the unsubscribe
that just kind of removes the observer
that corresponds to the subscription.
There's also a constructor for
a subscription, so
you can give it a function that returns
units that's just as a side effect and
you get back a subscription.
Now the interesting part of subscriptions
is that they form an interesting algebra.
Okay?
So
there's at least three kinds
of subscriptions in RX.
The first one is a composite
subscription and
that represents a group of subscriptions
that this unsubscribed together.
So you kind of, you know,
pull all your subscriptions together.
And when you unsubscribe
the outer subscription,
all the inner subscriptions
get unsubscribed.
The second one is the multiple
assignment subscription,
which is a subscription that
you can kind of, you know,
replace it's called multiassignment
subscription, sorry.
So you can replace the underlying
subscription and then there's the serial
subscription, which is a special case
of a multiassignment subscription.
But where you kind of resubscr,
when you subscribe another one,
then the underlying subscription,
the previous one gets unsubscribed.
Okay?
Whereas here, it just gets swapped out.
Let's look at a concrete example.
I create a new subscription.
This call unsubscribe, this will
print bye, bye, I'm gone fishing.
When go subscribe again,
it will do nothing.
So we assume that
subscriptions are item potent.
So when you call them
the action happens once,
then the subscription is unsubcribed.
You call unsubscribe again and
nothing happens.
And that's the reason that we have this
unsubscribe, is unsubscribed state,
because there's a big difference
between a subscription that is still,
you know, yet to be unsubscribed and a
subscription that is already unsubscribed.
But typically, it's item potent.
All right.
Here's another example where we are kind
of, you know, doing the same thing, but
then, we're printing isUnsubscribed.
In this case, it will return false.
And in this case, it will return true.
So, after you unsubscribe calling
isUnsubscribed will return true.
Here's an simple example of
a composite subscription.
As I said, it's a group of subscriptions.
So, if I have subscriptions A and B,
I add them to my composite subscription.
I ask are you unsubscribed?
It says, no, because, you know,
it's not yet unsubscribed.
Now, I unsubscribe the composite and
now the inner ones will be unsubscribed.
And what happens you can ask yourself now,
imagine that I have a composite
subscription that's already unsubscribed.
And now, I add a new subscription to that,
subscription C.
What will happen?
Well, the, the giant choice we
made is that when you add a new
subscription to an already
unsubscribed composite subscription,
that new subscription will
immediately be unsubscribed.
Here, it's so that's kind of what happens.
So, if it's not yet
subscribed, nothing happens.
If it's already unsubscribed,
it will be immediately unsubscribed.
Here's an example of
the multiassignment subscription.
We have a multiassignment
subscription that has A.
When we swap it out for
C, nothing happens to A.
When we unsubscribe it,
then again when we add C to it,
she will be immediately unsubscribed and
that's what we see here.
And the the the last one,
the serial subscription
as I said is where you're
immediately unsubscribed
the underlying subscription.
So that was the,
the algebra of subscriptions.
In general, you know,
typically the subscriptions are used
not in user code, but
when you implement your own operator.
And we will see later when we
talk about the creation of,
of observable sequences there.
The notion of subscription comes in.
But otherwise,
what you typically get is, you know,
you subscribe to something and
you get a subscription.
And sometimes, you combine them
if you want to pass it around.
But in general, you know, the,
this whole algebra of subscriptions
is used inside other operators.
All right?
So this was a short brief
introduction to subscriptions.
I invite you to play around with them.
There will be a couple of
exercises in the labs about them.
And hope you're having fun.
Thank you.