Hey welcome back everybody.
Last time we talked about creating
observable streams using the apply and
the create methods.
But if you recall the lecture
on creating futures,
there we used this concept of promises.
And as it turns out there's
a corresponding concept for observables.
And they're, they're called
subjects instead of promises.
And in this lecture we will drill
down a little bit into subjects and
compare and contrast with promises.
So let's refresh our
memory what promises are.
Here's a use of promises to implement map.
So what we did is into,
implement map over future.
So we want to this is
defined on future of T,
we take a function from T to S, and
we have to return a future of S.
And the way we did that is by
creating a new promise wait for
the future, the this, to complete.
If its completed successfully,
we would call f.
We had to kind of, you know,
wrap this around a try catch.
Because, you know, the f can fail too.
This is the thing that we didn't do when
we implemented a map for observables.
We ignored error cases here but
then we returned the future
corresponding to a promise.
So, a promise is an object
that has a future, all right.
But then there's no kind of interface,
special interface you know,
to describe just the fact
that you can set the future.
Okay or you can complete the future.
In rx we did that slightly different,
so here's the promise recap, so
there's a, we have a promise.
You can get the future of the promise and
then you can complete
the promise and you can listen on
the future with onComplete and
then you get the passing
the call back Try of T to unit.
Right?
So you could say a promise has a future.
Now in,
I actually already have two interfaces.
This is the Observer side where you
can kind of you know, pump in a value.
And, this is the Observable side.
So, the corresponding concept
in rx is a Subject, and
a Subject is an Observer and
an Observable.
So, you can subscribe on the one side.
And you can kind of push in
values on the other side.
Now, there's two big
differences with promises.
The first thing is that,
you know, we can also
we have these extra methods to complete
the subject but uncomplete it.
And there's onError and onNext.
And remember that with promises,
if you would try to call a complete twice,
and you would call it on
an already completed promise.
It would throw an exception and
there you had to use try complete.
In Subject, when a Subject has
been completed with onComplete or
onError, and if you then call any of these
methods again, they will just do nothing.
Okay, they won't throw.
So I think that's a slightly simpler
design, because then you don't have
to kind of think about, like, do I do,
use Try, onNext, or whatever.
No, you just do onNext.
And if the subject has already been
closed by one of the terminal methods,
the value is just dropped on the floor.
Okay?
But what happens is when you subscribe on
this side, when you call onNext that value
is propagated through all the subscribers.
So in some sense,
the subject is very much like a channel.
A channel where on the one side you can
pump in values that you can receive on
the other side.
So that's the picture here.
So let's look at our code.
And there are several kinds of subjects.
So in this case we are using
the PublishSubject,
which is the simplest one
that's just a simple pipe.
So here we create a PublishSubject,
that's the channel
we subscribe to it by and,
and print things out.
And then when we push 42 on the channel
42 will be delivered on those guys.
Now we unsubscribe one of them and
then now that subscriber will
not receive any more values.
We push the next value and
that will be kind of delivered here, and
now we complete the channel.
We subscribe to it with c, and
what we will see is that c
now immediately will and
get onCompleted and
we will get onCompleted as well.
And when we go onNext
again nothing will happen,
it will just be dropped on the floor.
But what is interesting is that
when you subscribe to a channel
to a PublishSubject that has already been
closed, you will get the onCompleted.
And similarly, you will get the onError.
Now one of the things that you
may have thought of is that.
When you're using this PublishSubject,
you're missing all the values.
When you subscribe later, when you're
too late, you only get the kind of,
you know, all the new values, but you,
you don't see any of the history.
And for that, we have a ReplaySubject,
and the ReplaySubject has a m,
memory of all the values that has,
have been pushed into it.
And when you subscribe later to it,
it will replay all those values.
Now course that's a little
bit dangerous because
it means that a ReplaySubject
should have unbounded memory.
And there's several overloads of
ReplaySubjects where you can say,
you know,
only remember the last thousand values or
only remember the last five
minutes of values and so forth.
Now the ReplaySubject is used
a lot in Rx Android where,
you know, if you're,
if you're doing some actions you want to,
might want to save some values
as you're making a transition.
And then when you resubscribe, you,
you don't want to lose any values there.
So i, it has very practical uses.
And then the other subjects that
we have are the async subject,
and the AsyncSubject
caches the final value.
So if you have a stream,
it just remembers the final value.
So it's a little bit like a future.
But where the last value is the,
the value of the async subject.
And then there's the behavior subject
that caches the latest value,
so when you kind of subscribe to that
you're getting the latest value.
And that kind of behaves
like a behavior if you have
ever heard of FRP behaviors.
And the behavior subject is,
corresponds to that.
Okay, so
this is a brief introduction to subjects.
I often recommend against using
subjects for two reasons.
First of all subjects
are like mutable variables.
As I said you're going to, you know,
you're, you're pushing
things in on one side.
You're receiving things on the other side.
They don't play very well with
the notion of back pressure.
Which is something that we will only
touch upon in the jam sessions.
But it's better to kind of, there's
also overload to publish that don't use
a subject but, you know,
are defined on a stream.
And where you pass in a function
that gets an Observable.
And then you can subscribe multiple times.
So, the overload of publish that uses
a function is the one that you should use.
But, in most cases you
don't need subjects.
And if you're find
yourself needing a subject
you can probably rewrite
your code not to use it.
Okay?
So but sometimes they are very useful,
just like sometimes a little bit of
mutable state is very convenient.
All right.
Thank you so much and
see you in the next lecture.