Hello, everybody.
Since, we have just a limited time to to
discuss a huge surface area,
the Rx surface area.
We have no time to discuss all
the intimate details about Rx, so
here what we're doing now is we're going
to give you a little bit of a Potpourri of
kind of, small things concerning
Rx that might be interesting.
But again, I would really advise you
if you want to learn more about Rx, and
more in depth that you kind of
you look at the Rx wiki, or
the ReactiveX io site,
where you can find a lot more information.
All right, let's look at this example
here in the earthquakes example,
we used this constructor, the Observable
dot from that took a Future.
When we were doing the reverse geocoding,
so that the reverse geocoding returned
a Future, and we wanted to turn that
into an Observable, and I just kind of
use that without, you know, thinking
too much, or saying too much about it.
But I think, it's interesting to see,
how we can implement that, and
we're going to implement that using an,
a sync subject,
which I said,
was very much like a Future because
it has only one value, or very much like a
promise, I should say, because, you know?
I can set it and it has only one value.
So, here's the code for
using the the apply constructor for here
on Observables with overloading it with
a Future, and we get back an Observable.
Since, we are in this case,
we want to remember the last
value of our stream.
What we're going is we're going to create
an AsyncSubject, and then when the Future
is complete,
what were going to do is we're going to
look at the two cases if the Future
completes with an error,
we're going to complete
the AsyncSubject with an error.
If the future completes with success were
going to call on next on the subject,
and then immediately complete it.
Now, what this gives us is
the behavior that we want
from a Future is that it
only executes once, right?
When you, when you, kind of,
you know, pass a call back, the un,
the complete call back, the uncomplete
call back to the Future, you know,
if you pass it multiple times, the
underlying computation is run only once.
And that's the behavior that we get
here by using the AsyncSubject.
So, if you subscribe to this subject,
it will always kind of give you the last
value without rerunning the computations.
Right?
It's a subtle
side effects are always subtle.
You have to think hard about them to make
sure that they don't get duplicated, or
that things get run more than once.
So, this code here is quite subtle,
and therefore, you know,
you shouldn't write these things yourself.
The Rx library has most of these operators
where, you know, all the details
are taken care of, for you such that
you don't have to worry about that.
Now, the other thing if we
look at the class Try of T,
what we see is that really
the two cases of success, and
failure were represented
by data structures, okay?
And if you remember one of the very,
very first lectures, where I said,
oh, but if you get a function
that takes a Try of T as a,
a parameter, the first thing you're going
to do is you're going to pattern match
on these two cases, and
you're going to use to functions.
One that takes a T to unit, say, and the
other one that takes a Throwable to unit.
So, instead, of materializing
the Try of T into a data structure,
and then destructing it
using pattern matching,
you might as well immediately
pass the two functions.
But, of course, maybe in Rx,
you want to do the same as Try of T.
You want to materialize the Notifications.
So, instead of, you know,
passing three call backs,
you might want to get an Observable, just
like you want to get the Future of Try,
you want to get an Observable
of something that represents,
you know, OnNext,
OnError, and OnCompleted.
And for that,
we have the idea of a Notification, so
a Notification is either OnNext,
OnError, and OnCompleted.
So, that's a data
structure that represents
the signal that sent on an Observable.
And there's a function here materialize,
that takes an observable of T, and
turns it into an Observable
of Notification of T.
All right?
And now, when you subscribe to this thing,
you get, you have to put,
your subscription has to pass a function
from Notification of T to unit,
just as what you got toward the Future.
Okay?
So, you can always kind of
move between these two things.
So, pattern matching, or
passing the function separately.
It's all the same thing.
It's whatever you feel
most comfortable with.
Okay, so here's a marble diagram for
materialize, and, you know,
we materialize this thing.
We see we get two onNext
followed by an onComplete, and
then the funny thing is that,
that stream completes itself.
So, there's two onCompletes because
there's the onComplete that's
materialized, but now,
this materialized stream also completes.
Okay.
Now, the other things that we had
with Futures was that we could block,
and remember, I said that was really bad,
you should never block because once you
block, you know,
all the asynchrony basically, evaporates.
And, the same is true for Observables,
once you are in Observable land everything
should stream, you should never block.
But sometimes, you know, for
whatever reason, probably, you want to do
debugging, or you want to do a little
demo script, you want to block.
And for that,
we have an operator called toBlocking.
And you know, really it should be called
toBlocking is unsafe make sure that,
you know what you're doing,
if you're using this operator,
something kind of ridiculous like that,
but, you know?
We just called it toBlocking, and
what this returns is a blocking
Observable that has ce,
certain kind of convenience
methods defined on it.
And this kind of, you know, just blocks
until the Observable is done and
here's an example.
So, we're going to do interval take(5).
We say, toBlocking, and
then we can do a list, and
then we can print the list, and,
or we can say, toBlocking, and
make sure that's a single value, and
if it's not one element, it, it will true.
All right, but again, the,
you should really not be using
toBlocking except, for
small demo programs.
So, and, you know, you can look in
the IntelliSense when you do toBlocking,
or what matches there are.
And but,
I really recommend against using this.
Once you're in a streaming
Asynchronous world,
you should never block in the first place.
Okay, the next thing is some of
the higher order operators that
are available on interval, as well.
And you might have questioned why,
where is reduce?
Where, or where is fault left,
and fault right?
And the thing is again,
if you're in a Asynchronous world,
reducing a value to a scalar type
doesn't make a lot of sense.
So, for example, if I want to
reduce a stream to a single value.
Well, this stream might be infinite.
You know, or you want to kind of you know,
it's like you have wait for
a long time until you
get the resulting value.
And so, you'd,
you usually don't use re, reduce a lot.
And another difference is that,
in just like a SQL,
when you do a reduction on a table,
you get back a table with a single row.
And the same here, when in Rx,
you reduce a stream to a single value,
you don't get a scalar, you get
an Observable that has that single value.
All right?
Whereas, with interval,
when you reduce it, you will get a scalar.
But here in this case we say, you know,
once you're in the Observable monad,
there's no way to escape,
except, via toBlocking, and then
you make it explicit that you're doing
something bad, and something dangerous.
As a last example, I want to show you, how
to create an Observable from an interval.
All right?
And then, of course, you can also go
from an interval, from an Observable
to an interval with toBlocking, but
I want to kind of go the other way now.
Okay?
So, but
in some sense,
you can go in both directions.
And here, what we do is we're using
the apply method that takes a subscriber,
and returns Unit.
And what we typically do here is we're go,
just going to kind of take the interval,
we're for reaching over it, and
as long as we're not unsubscribed
we're going to call onNext,
when we're done we call onCompleted.
Now, this can lead to problems
because imagine that, you know?
I have now, I subscribed to this,
running on a different thread.
Now, the consumer might be
much slower than the producer.
Okay?
And in that case, it means,
that we have to do unlimited buffering.
For that Rx has a notion of Backpressure,
and again,
that's outside the scope of this course,
but
in the gem sessions, we will have
a demo to show you how easy it
is to add that Backpressure
support in these cases.
All right?
And you can also go to the RX wiki,
and there's a whole section
that explains all the strategies
that you can use to do Backpressure.
So, that's the case where the consumer,
and
the producer are and
don't run at the same speed.
And you want to prevent build up
of unlimited internal buffers.
All right.
Thanks.
That was already again, the end of the,
our RX Potpourri and see you next week.