Welcome everybody to
already the last lecture
in the series about the four
essential effects of programming.
What I want to do in this last lecture
is talk about the observable contract.
And that's the behavioral
contract about observable streams
that is not visible in the type.
The type signatures of observable and
observer, and specifically of observer,
just says that, you know, you, you know,
you pass three call backs on next,
on completed and on error and
they get called.
But nothing in that signature tells
you in what order they are called or
what the guarantees are.
And similarly, when you subscribe to an
observable, you get back a subscription.
We did look at the algebra
of subscriptions, but
we didn't talk about,
you know, what's you know,
what the observable stream
does with the subscriptions.
And we're going to drill down a little
bit into that in this lecture.
And the lesson of this lecture
is that you should never
ever implement observer or
observable yourself.
You should always use the factory
methods that the library provides,
because if you do it yourself there's
a very, very high probability
that you don't satisfy the contract and
something will go wrong.
So, that's really what I want
to kind of drill in your heads.
Don't ever implement observable or
observer yourselves, and
the same for subscription, and
the same for all Rx types.
Only use the factory methods
that the library provides.
So, let's kind of see why
this is not trivial, okay?
So, here is a, example of, you know,
how you naively could implement,
observable.create.
So, remember, observable.create takes
a function from observer to subscription.
And it needs to create a new observable.
Well, you can say, that's easy.
Because I just define subscribe,
that takes an observer.
Oh and I have a function
that takes an observer and
returns a subscription as subscribe,
should return a subscription.
Oh, then I can just pass the observer
to that function to get
the subscription and I'm done.
Well, it would be great if life was so
easy, but that's not the case.
So if you look at
the actual implementation,
there's a lot of implementation
details here that are wrapped around
the function, and the kind of
passing of the observer, to ensure
that our Rx contract that we're talking
about in this lecture is satisfied.
On the other hand, if you're using
observable.create, when you're
reasoning about it, it is kind of pretty
safe to kind of just unfold it like this.
So when you do observable.create
with some function, and
you subscribe to that with an observer,
you can kind of say that's more or
less the same as call,
passing the observer to that function.
Okay?
But there's still all that
implementation detail.
But this is the conceptual model.
But it's, the actual
implementation is not this simple.
And the same is true for
the observable apply,
which took a function that takes
a subscriber and returns unit.
So when we subscribe to that,
we get an observer.
So now, at least,
we must wrap the observer in,
in something to make it a subscriber,
pass it to F, and
then there's also a lot of
kind of implementation details
that wrap around this to insure
that the contract is satisfied.
Now, what is this contract?
I may have mentioned this
word now several times.
So let's look at one thing.
So, one thing is,
is the behavior of the subscription
that you get out of subscribe.
And in Rx, we implement the so
called auto-unsubscribe behavior.
That means that if,
in this case I took here,
if you call on complete on this observer,
or you can call uncomplete, or on error
on the subscriber that gets passed in,
that the subscription that gets handed
out is automatically unsubscribed.
So here's how you can test that.
So here we implement observable.empty.
So as we know it took a subscriber and
it immediately calls onCompleted.
Now we say s equals empty.unsubscribe and
then when we print it's unsubscribed.
We will see that it is immediately true
even though we have not
unsubscribed from s.
But the reason is that, you know, there's
the auto unsubscribe behavior here.
And notice, I promise you there
would be typos in the slides.
And there is obviously an equals
sign here in white ink.
It's there, I promise you.
[LAUGH] But it's just in white ink so
you can't see it.
All right, so here are some other
issues with the Rx contract.
Since you know, there's these three call
backs, onNext, onError, and onCompleted.
We guarantee that they are called
in a certain order, so we are,
we guarantee that the stream
has to follow an structure.
So we call onNext zero or more times and
then optionally we call onCompleted or
onError.
So it might be that in the case of never,
that nothing is called.
So that's yeah,
never calling anything, that is a,
a, a valid intent of this expression.
Or you can call onNext,
you know, multiple times, but
never call onCompleted, onError.
Or you can call the normal case onNext
many times followed by onCompleted.
Or you can call onCompleted
directly that was empty.
Or onError directly and it was error.
All right?
But it's always in this sequence.
So after you've seen an onCompleted or
an onError, you will never see
any of the other methods anymore.
So, once onCompleted has been called,
you can be sure that onNext,
onCompleted and onError are never called.
And that's the reason that we do this
auto-unsubscribe because we know that
the the stream is done and so
we kind of eagerly unsubscribe for you.
So these are the two kind of,
you know, valid instances.
There's a number of onNext
followed by onCompleted.
followed by onError,
and of course there could be no onError or
onNext.
The last part of the Rx contract is
the fact that onNext and onCompleted and
onError are called sequentially so
there will never be overlap in goals.
So they, they are always serialized.
so if you get here on onNext,
the next onNext will only be called
when the first onNext will be finished.
So there's never overlap.
So you'd, inside your callbacks,
you never have to kind of,
you know, worry about concurrency.
Because the Rx library
serializes everything for you.
And if you look at the implementation,
you will see that we go to great lengths
not to use locks, but try to do everything
lock free, to make that efficient.
So, maybe another way to look
at Rx is to take a fancy
library that kind of takes
care of serialization and
of concurrent notifications for you.
I don't, we don't have time to go into
all the, details of the Rx Contact.
And all the kind of, you know,
API, API design guidelines.
But you can go to either the,
reactive X website, or
the Rx wiki, or there's the original,
the bible of Rx the Rx Design Guidelines.
If you google for Rx design guidelines,
you get a PDF document,
that explains the guidelines
in terms of Rx.net.
But they are all valid for
every implementation of Rx.
So, let me finish by saying that Rx here,
in this course,
we showed you Rx,
Scala that's based on Rx Java.
As I warned you, the names in Rx Scala
are often different, the identifiers and
method names are different than in
Rx Java but the semantics are the same.
We just made sure that the API feels
natural for Scala programmers.
But on the JVM we have a whole
slew of implementations.
Rx Java, there's bindings for
for closure, for groovy
you name it, any language that
runs on the JVM has Rx bindings.
And then there's also ports
of Rx in other languages.
In Rx Java, in fact,
there's a port of the original Rx.net.
And there's Rx for C++,
also very popular is Rx for JavaScript.
But there's also Rx for
Python, Rx for Ruby, and
there's reactive Coco done by,
the friendly people at GitHub that is
an implementation of Rx for objective C.
So all the concepts that you
learned in this lecture,
you can apply in any language.
So you're not kind of stuck with Scala or
.NET or with Java.
It's the general principals
applied to any language and
the framework has been forwarded to any
other language and often, you know,
when you're building a web application
your client is written in JavaScript.
You can use RxJS there,
your server side is written in Java and
you use RxJava or RxCala there,
there and then you can communicate.
Okay, so, one last warning: never
ever implement observable or
observer yourself, or in fact,
any of the other Rx types.
Because, you know,
you will violate the Rx contract.
I guarantee you.
Now, when you do a code review and
you see somebody kind of write
now if code like this, right?
They say, oh, I need to create
an observable just by kind of, you know,
implementing this subscribe method,
that alarm bells should go off.
You should never ever do that.
Okay?
So really use only the factory methods.
Okay, thank you so
much for your attention,
I hope that you enjoyed these lectures.
And I want to again remind
you here one last time
about the four effects of programming.
The first column here was
computations that return one value.
If they do that synchronously,
we started out with blocking methods that
didn't kind of, you know, in their type
show that there could be an exception.
And then we introduced a trimonet
that made exceptions explicit.
All right?
Then we went from Try and said hey,
now there's also the effect of latency.
Remember the table where, you know,
sending a packet from Europe, to,
from the US to Europe and
back would take several years.
So we have to make latency
explicit In our types.
And for that, we used future of T,
which represents a computation that
can fail and takes you a long time.
And there we talked about a lot of
combinators on futures etcetera, and
we introduced asynch await.
And asynch await, allowed us to
still write normal control flow and
the reason that we can do that is
because futures return only one value.
Then these two here were related by
the magic trick of duality where we
reverse the arrows.
And then we moved from, you know,
the one side to the many sides, and
we start it with iterable.
Those are the synchronous streams where
you're pulling values out of the streams.
And that's my block, so
say that you're pulling strings out
of a file that will take, you know,
in human time days or months or
years, so you should never do that.
And so we reuse the dualization trick
here to go from iterables to observables.
And we talked quite at length about also,
all the higher order functions and
details of observables.
'Kay?
So, I hope that, you know,
you can apply this knowledge in
your day to day programming.
I hope that it gave you a little
bit more insight in the essence of,
you know, effect.
And so I leave you here with my motto,
happy hacking.
And, you know, use the force.
Bye bye.