The error kernel pattern allows us to
keep important actors relatively safe.
But there are cases where we
need to not lose state at all.
We need to persist it.
In this lecture,
we look at how actors can do that.
The first observation is that
losing state due to a restart
is not the only thing which can happen.
Not only our software can be buggy,
our hardware can make mistakes too.
For example,
the computer's power supply might fail, or
there might be a power outage in the whole
region and the data center goes down.
In that case,
the running state of actors will be
lost because it is only kept in memory.
If we need to keep that state across,
for example the power outage,
then we need to make sure that it is
stored on a hard drive, for example.
When the power comes back on, we can
then read the last persisted state, and
start from there.
The same principle applies when it comes
to a softer source of the restart.
The reason why we did it
might be different, but
what needs to be done is exactly the same.
We need to store the result
of successful processing, and
once the failure has happened when we
recover from it, we need to recreate
the current running state, so that we
can keep running from where we left off.
There are two main ways in
which state can be persisted.
The first is to have the actor mirror,
a persistent storage location,
and do in place updates of both.
So when the actor's state changes,
the persistent location is also updated.
This persistent location could
be files in the file system,
or it could also be a record
in a relational database.
The other way is to not persist
the state itself and update it,
but to persist the changes
which are applied to state.
And this is done in an append only
fashion, meaning that these change
records will never be deleted,
they will only be added to.
The current state can then be derived by
reapplying old changes from the beginning.
There are obvious benefits to persisting
the state and doing in-place updates.
The first is that recovery of the latest
state can be done in constant time,
because you just need to go to that
one memory location and read it back.
The other advantage is that
the data volume needed for
storage depends only on the number of
records and not on their rate of change.
It is easy to see that if
you persist the changes,
you will always persist at least as much.
And most of the time,
much more data than if you would
just persist the records themselves.
But there are also benefits
to persisting the changes.
For example, if you do that,
you can go back to any point in time and
replay history.
Audit what happened in which order,
or restore a certain state,
say from last Thursday because you need
to either rerun what has happened or
you need to discard all the changes
which have been done since then.
During a replay, the code which handles
the processing could also have,
for example, been fixed,
because it had a bug previously.
And that means that errors which
correct into the current state
can be corrected retroactively.
This is not possible if you
only store the current state,
because it will have the bug in it.
You all have seen the third
advantage at work.
For example,
if you were shopping at a large
shopping site on the internet,
which we all well know.
If you look at the shopping cart, and
you put an item in, it is in the shopping
cart, you might continue shopping,
take it out, replace it by another one.
And finally, once you go to the checkout,
the current contents of the shopping
cart is what you are actually buying.
If you only persist that,
then the whole history is lost.
But it might be very
interesting to keep statistics.
For example, this refrigerator has
been replaced in 50% of the cases
by that other one, and people can then
learn from other people's decisions.
Of course, these insights can also
be used inside the company itself
to organize their logistics processes.
Storing all these events
takes a lot of space, but
space is comparatively cheap nowadays,
and therefore,
if profit can be made from analyzing
these data, then it's well worth it.
The fourth advantage has to do
with hardware and how that works.
If you write to an append only stream,
you can write a much higher bandwidth
to IO, to network devices and
also to hard disks.
The reason is, that in-place
updates need to at least appear to
occur in exactly the order
in which they were given.
Which limits the possibilities for
optimization.
Finally, persisting immutable data
has the advantage we have seen throughout
the functional programming course.
Anything which cannot possibly change
can be freely shared and replicated.
There is no need to synchronize access.
And whether you store
an event stream to one, two,
or three locations does
not make a difference.
This point allows the benefits of
both approaches to be combined.
Consider an actor which
wants to persist its state.
It writes events describing all
the changes into a event log.
Since this log is immutable,
another process
could take this data and
feed them into a database offline.
From which the actor could then
retrieve the latest persistent
state in constant time.
Doing that for all changes can be
the right answer in certain situations.
For example, if there are multiple
readers for that state and
not only this actor, but if you only want
to persist the state of an actor and
put an upper bound on the time a recovery
may take, then you can also use snapshots.
So we have again our actor,
producing the stream of changes.
And then to the side,
there are snapshots, which it tags.
At this state, when it persists
that event, that was my state.
And it can do so periodically,
to keep the time short between these.
And if recovery is needed, then only
the latest snapshot will be taken and
all events which came after that.
Snapshots, again, have the property that
they are immutable so they can be written,
append in an efficient fashion and
they can be freely shared.
With this background, we can look at how
actors actually persist the changes.
You can picture an actor that is
persistent as one that keeps taking notes
of things that are happening, things that
it is doing or things that it wants to do.
In this is made available
by the persist method.
We'll see the logic context in a minute.
It is important to first learn
what it means to persist an event.
First of all,
we must create the event itself.
Let's say we have a class MyEvent that
we construct with some arguments here.
Passing this into the first
argument list of the persist method
means that this event is sent
to the so-called journal.
We have here our actor that
wants to persist things.
And in the system, we have another actor
that understands a certain set of
messages related to persistence.
Calling the persist method means
sending a message to this journal
that we want to persist a certain event.
The journal can be implemented
in many different ways.
It could write this to the local hard disk
which would not be perfect in
case that hard disk fails.
So typically, it will also write it to
some other hard disk somewhere else or
it might be stored in a different fashion.
It might be in databases
that are held in many copies
in memory across all the globe.
It can be any system that can make sure
that whatever they pass here, the event
that we want to persist is actually
held such that it will not vanish.
And that it is always there.
Once that has been done,
once that has been confirmed that
the event has been written to disk and
replicated and
so on, the journal will reply to
the actor with a confirmation.
This confirmation contains the event.
So the event travels once from the actor,
to the journal,
is being persisted, and
then travels back to the actor.
As soon as this journey is complete,
the second part of the persist method,
this function here comes into play.
We receive the event as it
comes back from the journal.
And now, whatever we do in here,
we can do in the knowledge that this
event is stored safely somewhere.
We can rely on the fact that we
can replay this event later.
We know that it has been persisted.
This is why we describe events
as facts about the past.
Things that are certain and commentating.
In order to look at
a more complete example,
we introduce a actor that
does something useful.
In this case,
it manages a set of block posts.
This actor understands
a command called NewPost.
Which contains the string, the text of the
blog post, and some ID, a correlation ID.
So that when the actor replies
either with a positive BlogPosted or
a negative BlogNotPosted message,
we can use this ID to find out which
posted was that was accepted or rejected.
In addition to this external
protocols spoken by the actor,
we also define a set of events
that this actor creates and emits.
The first one is taking notes
of a post that has been created.
And this is the PostCreated event
which holds the text of the blog post.
And the second one,
to make this actor a bit more interesting,
records when the user who has submitted
this blog post has reached their quota.
Let's say we have a really stupid
limit of you can only create one post.
We'll see it on the next slide.
The final piece here is that
the actor itself will keep state.
It accumulates the posts
that were created and
keeps track of whether
the quarter has been reached.
And this is held in a class called State
here, which holds all the blog posts and
the disabled flag once
the quota has been reached.
Remember that the purpose of
events is to describe change.
This means that the events themselves are
meaningful in the domain that we modeled.
So, we have blog PostCreated and
QuotaReached.
But the events themselves do not know how
this influences the state of the actor.
The state of the actor needs
to know how events change it.
This is why the State object has
an updated method which takes
an event and then it reacts accordingly
to what the event type was.
If it was a PostCreated,
we make a copy of the state depending
this text of the new blog post to
the posts that are already there.
Once we see a QuotaReached event,
we just switch on the disabled flag.
With these preparations out of the way,
we can take a look at the actor itself.
The first thing to note is that
instead of extending actor,
we extend PersistentActor.
This trait defines the persist
method that we have seen earlier.
And it also runs this process of sending
the to be persisted events to the journal,
and receiving them back when
they have been persisted.
In order to do this, the PersistentActor
must speak with the journal.
Must have a conversation that
we do not see in this actor.
This is why the receive method has been
implemented in the PersistentActor
already, and what has been written
there delegates to two new methods.
The receiveCommand method is
the correspondent of the receive in
a normal actor and that it defines
its normal behavior during runtime.
There is another receiveRecover
that we'll talk about later.
The crucial piece that defines
the stateful behavior of this actor
is kept in a single variable called state.
It starts out with a state that
has no blog posts in it and
is not in the disabled state.
When this actor receives
a request to create a new post,
this will contain a text and
this correlation ID.
And in this case, the actor checks if
posting has been disabled in this state,
then the reply is pretty clear.
We send a BlogNotPosted for this ID,
with a quota reached explanation in it.
The other case is
the more interesting one.
We want to create a blog post,
and we must take note of it.
So, first we create a PostCreated
event with the text,
and we persist that once this
event comes back from the journal,
we update the state of this actor.
I have written a utility
method here which does it.
And then we can confirm to the sender
of the new post request that
this blog has been posted.
In order to change the behavior
of this actor to one which is
preventing further block posts,
we also persist a QuotaReached event.
This demonstrates the usefulness
of this updateState
method which I find
myself writing typically.
Because this will just be expanded into
a function that takes an event and
applies it, so
we can use the name here just like that.
Now, what happens if this actor crashes,
if the machine crashes that it is run on.
When we start it again,
the actor will process everything
that it has persisted before.
And this is done in
the receiveRecover method.
So whatever was successfully persisted,
and it was post created, or
the quota reached, will afterwards be
replayed in this receiveRecover method.
And here we simply take the event and
update the state of this actor with it.
This means that the state of the actor
will go through all the same steps
that it has gone through previously.
UpdateState here and
an updateState there, and
the only thing that we leave out
in this process is the other
actions that are taken in response
to successful persistence of events.
While recovering,
the sender of that blog post
that we received from the journal
might not be there anymore.
This recovery might actually happen
several years after the blog has been
posted so
sending back to that sender is pointless.
But we need to update the state so
that we arrive at the same internal state
after recovery as we had before the crash.
There is one important detail that I
have glossed over on the last slide, and
it is best explained
using some flow diagrams.
So what have we implemented?
We have the actor and
time going downwards, and
we have the journal as
the interesting parties.
When the actor receives a new post,
we have done several things,
the first of which was to check whether
posting is currently enabled or not.
I'll mark that with
this red color here and
let us say the check was positive,
then we persisted the new blog post.
Now, it takes some time for the journal
to disseminate this event, to replicate
it to all the storage locations and
to get back with the acknowledgement.
Let's say it happens here.
At this point,
the function was run that we gave to
the persist method as the second argument.
And this was updating the internal state,
as well as sending the reply
to the original requester.
So let's say this is updating the internal
state, and then we send back Blog Posted.
Now the interesting question is,
what happens with a request
that comes in in between these?
When using the persist method to make
this round trip via the journal,
the persistent actor trait switches
this actor in a sort of deaf state or
in a state where it does
not receive new messages.
This means that the new post message
that came in at this point in time
will not be handled until the previous
process has been completed.
This is necessary because this
check here depended on the state
being the current state, but
we only update the state down here.
So if we perform this check again here,
we will find that the quota
reached has not yet been applied.
We will persist another blog post even
though that was not supposed to happen.
This is why the processing of this message
is deferred internally until this point.
There is another method that can be used,
so we'll draw the second case.
We have, again, the actor and
the journal and their timelines.
We have a NewPost coming in.
We perform the check, and
then we use a method called persistAsync.
This will also carry out the whole round
trip for the event through the journal.
So, it will come back at some point here,
but
it will not stop the actor from processing
other messages in the meantime.
This means in order to keep the actor's
processing consistent with our rules,
we need to apply the changes here,
already.
Such that when the next post comes in,
it will be rejected because
the quota reached has been applied.
Now what is left to do when the
persistence round trip has been completed,
and the event's come
back from the journal?
In this case,
the state has already been updated, so
the only thing that is needed is the Blog
Posted message to the original requester.
The difference between these two schemes
of doing things becomes more clear
if we consider that the quota will
only be reached after the 1000th
blog post and not after the first one.
This means that most of the time,
this check will be successful,
and we will want to
accept a new blog post.
In this case,
accepting a blog post is always deferred
until the previous one has been completed.
This means that this round
trip time through the journal
determines the maximum rate at
which we can accept new commands.
In the persistAsync case on
the other hand, we can go ahead and
have several new post
commands outstanding.
The round trip will be made, that
defines the latency between new post and
blog posted, but other things can
be happening at the same time.
This means that the maximum
throughput of this actor for
processing new blog posts will be much
higher than in the left-hand side case.
The obvious question is,
if it performs better,
why do we not always
just use this approach?
Well, if you look at the history
that these graphs express, you can
see that this actor here will always only
be in states that have been persisted.
It only changes the state once
recovery will lead to the same result.
If this actor crashes in here,
then it had reached a state
here which was never persisted.
This means this can only work if
this new internal state change here,
which is not yet fully committed, cannot
have any externally visible effects.
For example, we must not reply
to this new post that comes in
here before we have actually heard
back from the journal at this point.
There are many use cases which
can benefit from this, but
keep in mind that this is
not a general solution.
There is one more aspect that
these graphs can illustrate.
Let's say the whole system
fails at this point.
For example,
there is a power outage in the computing
center and everything goes down.
It is clear that the Blog Posted
messages will not have been sent,
not in either case.
But it is not clear whether the change,
the event,
has already has been written to disk and
will, therefore, be replayed or not.
What this means is that the persistent
location to which the journal
writes the events, becomes the one
source of truth for this system.
Either it has been persisted,
then it will be replayed.
Or it has not been persisted, and
then the post has never been posted.
This is a fundamental aspect
of distributed systems.
You can have only one source of truth
because agreeing whether the post
has been posted between
this storage location.
And the client that wanted the post to
be posted is a process that takes time.
It is not an atomic action that
can be either made or not.
The practical consequence is that
the client which sent the new post is
either interested in having the post made
and then it will wait for the blog posted,
and if it doesn't come, it will resend
it for that purpose it had the ID.
Or, that client might not care anymore,
and then it will not resend and
then the storage
location in the journal just determines
whether the blog post was made or not.
In order to complete this, let us look at
the code that corresponds to the second
way of doing things, using persistAsync.
In this case, we do the check first,
then we create the event and
update the state accordingly.
And then we use persistAsync to send
the creative event to the journal and when
it comes back we can reply to the original
sender that the blog has been posted.
And we also need to cycle the quota
reached from the Journal.
But when it comes back,
there is nothing else for
us to do because the state
change has already been applied.
When discussing that in
a distributed system
you cannot have a distributed source
of truth, they will just be one.
We'd already touched on the subject that
if someone is interested in something else
happening somewhere else, then that
someone needs to make sure of that,
needs to retry things.
This leads us to wanting better
messaging guarantees in the at-most-ones
semantics that Accra and other actor
implementations provide out of the box.
What we want is that the message is sent,
and then resent if something got lost,
until it was successfully delivered
this is called At-Least-Once delivery.
In order to implement this, the sender and
the receiver of the message
need to collaborate.
The sender needs to be able to resend
the message until it gets the confirmation
back and the recipient, of course,
needs to provide that confirmation.
It needs to acknowledge
the receipt of the message.
Otherwise the sender doesn't
know when it can stop resending.
Now messages can be lost in any direction
in this exchange and if the receipt
confirmations are lost, then the sender
will faithfully continue sending messages.
So At-Least-Once does not only mean
that messages are sent possibly
multiple times, they will also be
received possibly multiple times.
So this is what At-Least-One entails.
But how does this relate
to actor persistence?
Well, if you need to be able to retry
something, you need to take note of that
because If the actor that
wants to retry things crashes,
the machine crashes, and so on.
Then after I just restart it, it needs to
remember that it was about to do something
and this is not only true for
the messages that need to be resent,
and keeping track of that,
that shall happen.
It must also encompass
the acknowledgements
because the actor must also
remember when to stop resending.
Here we look at a simplified
version of our blog post
management actor that manages
the blog post for one user.
This one extends PersistentActor
as the previous one.
But it also mixes in
the At-Least-Once Delivery trait.
This trait provides the deliver method.
Now, when a new post request comes in,
we persist that we want
this post to be created, and when that has
been written to the journal and the event
comes back, We tell the At-Least-Once
Delivery trait that we want to deliver
a PublishPost command, containing
the text, to a certain publisher.
Publisher is giving to this
UserProcessor actor as an ActorPath, and
not an ActorRef.
The reason for this is that,
and you may remember,
that an actor if is coupled to the life
cycle of one actor incarnation.
If the whole system crashed and
is restarted afterwards,
then the ActorRef in the old
system Will no longer be valid.
If you wrote them to disc and
read them back in, and
reconstruct the ActorRefs and try to send
to them the messages will go nowhere
because the actors will all have
been recreated from scratch.
The part of the actor identity that stays
valid across such an event is its name.
And that is exactly what is
captured in the ActorPath.
The other notable detail about
the delivery method is that the second
argument it takes is
not simply an event or
command it is a function that produces
one by inserting something here.
What it inserts is a long integer number
that serves as a correlation ID that we
will see how it's used in the following.
Now as I said, the actor needs to remember
that it wants to publish this post.
And it does that whenever it
sees its post creative message.
So we also need to run the same
processing in the receiveRecover method.
Normally you would update the state of the
actor in both cases which I left out of
this example.
It is just important to note that delivery
must be re-initiated after a crash.
But what about the confirmations?
We said that send and
receive any to collaborate.
Let us say that the publisher
speaks a protocol where
you can send a published post and
it will reply with a post published
confirmation which carries the same
ID that was placed in here.
What we do whenever we get that
acknowledgement, is that we inform the at
least once delivery traits that this
delivery has been confirmed with this ID.
And it is also important to do
the very same thing to your recovery.
Picture this actor crashing
after three years and
handling thousands of blog posts.
Then it will, for all of them,
see a PostCreated and
a PostPublished pair,
which means it will start redelivery
of something that was two years ago and
then immediately stop redelivering.
Of course the At-Least-Once Delivery
trait is smart enough so
that it does not actually start sending
the outstanding events or commands.
It waits until recovery is complete.
So deliver and confirm, deliver and
confirm means putting it in the lists
of things to be resend and taking it out
again and only what is still outstanding
after recovery finishes will
then be sent to the publisher.
When we talk about what messaging
solutions we need to provide,
which semantics they shall do us
At-Least-Once is not normally what we say.
Normally what we want to have
is when we send a thing,
then once the messaging
system takes this thing and
goes about sending it, we want
the messaging solution to make sure for
us that processing happens for
this item exactly once.
We can capture this in a little sketch
to make the responsibilities clear.
We have a sender and a recipient.
Between them, we have.
A way to transmit messages,
which has at-most-once semantics.
At-least-once is
the responsibility of the sender.
The sender needs to remember and
resend things.
Exactly-once is the responsibility
of the recipient.
The recipient needs to remember what it
has done and then avoid redoing it again.
In order to demonstrate this in code,
let us look at the publisher
that we sent our block post to.
This will be a PersistentActor,
because it needs to take note of
what it has already published.
The user processor used at-least-once
semantics to make sure that
the PublishPost messages
arrive at this point.
And now we need to implement
the deed application.
For this purpose,
an id is included in the PublishPost.
We're using here the ID that is generated
by the at-least-once delivery trait
because that starts at zero and
then is incremented contiguously.
When the publisher and
the user processor startup,
they will both start their
id sequence numbering at 0,
so we expert the first post
to have an id of 0 here.
When the PublishPost comes in,
we check the id to see
if it comes from the future and
this means that we need to ignore it.
It is something that is
newer than what we expect.
There is a message missing.
Otherwise, if the id is smaller than
the next expectedId, that means
that we previously confirmed this id, but
the confirmation must have been lost.
So we just need to confirm it again.
Otherwise, the id must
equal the expectedId, and
this is where the interesting
action happens.
First, we persist the event
that we published this post.
Only once this is committed to stable
memory, we get back this event,
we inform the sender of this confirmation.
And we do the actions of
actually publishing the post.
Let's say we modify some
website to do that.
As a last step,
we need to increment the expectedId so
that we can receive the next
PublishPost command.
This sequence makes sure that
we persist the PostPublished
exactly in sequence for
the IDs zero, one, two, and so on.
During recovery,
the only thing that we need to
do is to keep track of what
we have already published.
What we have already confirmed.
This process makes sure that we
will persist the PostPublished for
each ID exactly-once.
Now, what happens if the machine that this
actor is running on crashes at some point?
There are several different
points where this could happen.
It's rather interesting if it happens here
because we would ignore things anyway.
The most interesting part is
within these braces here.
Let us consider that the PostPublished
was persisted successfully.
We start executing the function, but
the machine crashes right here,
before we send the message.
This means the same thing as
if the acknowledgment that
we would normally send back
would have been lost on the way.
The sender will retry the message.
We will see this expectedId
is smaller as the one that we
expect because persistence was successful.
So we have during recovery
incremented the expectedId.
But what about the modifications
to the website?
These will not be retried.
They are the responsibility
of the publisher actor.
We have persisted
the confirmation here already, so
during replay,
we do not modify the website.
Again, that is the purpose of this block.
This demonstrates that exactly-once
delivery of messages is not
usually what you really want.
What you really want is
exactly-once processing
of the effects that these
messages should have.
This also should make it clear
that no messaging solution
can ever take care of this for you.
If the machine crashes
at the exact wrong time,
then the message may have been delivered.
But it has not yet had its effect.
The underlying issue is a fundamental one.
Performing an effect and
persisting that it was performed can,
in almost all cases,
not be done atomically.
You need to do either one then the other.
Or the other way around.
If you perform the effect
before persisting it,
then you achieve at-least-once semantics.
Because you might perform it,
the machine crashes, you have no
memory that you have performed it.
So you perform it again and
then you persist.
You have done it twice.
The other choice is what I
implemented on the previous slide,
namely to perform the effect of updating
the website after persisting that this
has been done, and this achieves,
as we have seen, at-most-once semantics.
Commercially available messaging solutions
usually pick the second of
these alternatives, but
if you have a choice, you should make it
based on your underlying business model.
What costs more, doing the effect
one too many, or one too few times?
This choice to be made is
usually between two evils.
If you think about,
you need to build a credit card, and
you want to do it exactly-once for
one purchase, as is usual.
Then, doing it zero times is maybe
just as bad as doing it two times.
In one case, the company loses money.
In the other case,
the customer will be very unhappy.
So is there not a third way?
The key to solving this
dilemma is called idempotency.
An action is idempotent if executing
it multiple times has the same effect
as executing it once, it does not matter
whether you repeat the action or not.
We have seen an example of
this on the previous slide,
where the actor assigned the expectedId.
No matter how many times
the actor restarts, and
makes the very same assignment,
the result is always the same.
Combining idempotent actions with
at-least messaging semantics
achieves effectively
exactly-once processing.
We have seen that actors
persist their state
by recording the changes that
they intend to make to it.
Each event is a fact that represents
knowledge about the past and
that can be freely replicated,
shared and sent around.
Other components can use the events
immediate by one to learn
of that other components progress and
make changes to its own state.
The state that existed at
any given point in the past
can be reconstructed by replaying
the events that lead up to that state.
Snapshots can be used to reduce
the time that this takes,
because if you use them, recovery does not
need to start at the beginning of time but
it can be started at
the most recent snapshot.
Keep in mind, though, that snapshots do
not represent the meaningful business
events of the domain, they represent
the internal state of a component.
As such, they are less durable and
less valuable than the events themselves.