We have seen what actors are and
how messages are passed between them, but
how does one go about actually
writing actor systems?
This is what we will look
at in the following, and
we will encounter a few other useful
things to use in the actor toolbox.
When starting to design an actor
application, it is helpful to visualize
first a room full of people, and you
have all these people at your disposal.
You have your task which you need to
solve, and what you need to figure out in
the process is how to divide the task
into subtasks and sub subtasks.
So that every person knows what to do,
and there is not too much to do for
any one of them.
Since actors have fairly low overhead,
you can create many of them.
So consider this group of people
to be of very large size for
all practical purposes.
As you know from organizing like a party
or anything where people collaborate on,
it is important to keep an eye on
who will have to talk to whom and
how much they will have to talk
in order to fulfill their tasks.
It is important to optimize
the communication paths in an actor system
just as it is in a human organization.
There is one aspect of this
comparison between actors and
people which does not quite hold.
And that is that actors, in contrast to
people, are easily spawned and terminated.
You can create as many of them as you want
in the process of solving your problem,
and they can be short lived,
just unlike people.
As you go about defining the tasks
of certain actors in your system and
the role they play and the other actors
they collaborate with, draw a diagram and
mark down the communication
lines between the actors and
how they relate to each other.
I will demonstrate this process
now on a simple project.
The problem which we want to solve
is to write an application which,
given a URL, it will go to the web,
retrieve the document, check for
links in it, and follow the links,
and repeat the process.
Up to a certain maximum depth, of course.
Otherwise, it would be boundless.
And all links encountered in the process
shall eventually be returned to
the one requesting that this be done.
How would you solve this
with a bunch of people?
There will be one actor which
we call Receptionist, and
this one is responsible for
accepting incoming requests.
These will come from some external Client.
This Receptionist is a person who
will just have the responsibility of
accepting your request noting
down that it shall be done,
noting who was the Client, and then
telling someone else to do the real job.
When traversing the web,
we will encounter many links, and
there might even be cycles.
So when we see a link which
we have already visited,
we need to stop there because
otherwise we run in an endless loop.
It is best that we assign one person
to the task of one such traversal
because that person will remember what
has already been visited and what not.
Translating that into an actor,
let's call it Controller.
This Controller will need help because its
main job is to remember what was visited
and what still needs visiting, but
it would be better if we had someone else
to do the actual visiting of a link and
to extract the information which we want.
So let's put in another
actor which we call Getter.
Getter is a rather simple one.
It will just go, look at one URL,
retrieve the document,
extract the links which are in there, and
then tell the Controller what it found.
The Controller can then spawn other
Getters to visit the new links and so on.
To recap, let us now put in the messages
which will be exchanged to achieve this.
The client sends a get request for a URL.
The Receptionist will
create a Controller and
send it a check for
a given URL with a certain depth,
because we do not want to do
this in a boundless fashion.
The Controller will then tell the Getter
to retrieve what is at that URL.
And the Getter will then reply
with possibly multiple links and
then finally a done message,
so that the Controller
knows that this Getter
has exhausted all which
was found at that URL.
All links which are found in the process
should be treated as quickly as possible,
and they can also be
retrieved in parallel.
So there will be multiple Getters,
which perform the subsequent
checking of the links in parallel.
The Controller will have to keep track of
which URL was encountered
at which search depth.
So let us say this comes
down at depth one,
then the links come back at depth one, but
when they are checked by the next Getter,
they will be at depth two, and so on.
It is best to keep this state
travelling with the message, so
that this request contains the depth,
and the responses contain the depth,
freeing the Controller from
having to remember all of this.
Once the depth is exhausted and
all Getters have sent their done messages,
the final result is communicated
to the Receptionist.
The Receptionist was the one who kept
track of which client requested which URL,
and it will send back the appropriate
response to the client.
This is the whole process which we
will implement in the following.
What we will do requires
the use of some web client.
I will be using the async-http-client
library, as given in this artifact here.
Then we need to write a Getter for
processing the body which was retrieved.
Then we step up one level
to write the Controller,
which takes care of the Getters and
all links encountered.
And finally we will think
about the Receptionist and
how that manages the Controller.
Let us start with the most simple example,
which is also given at the top of
the documentation for AsyncHttpClient.
First, we create an instance of
this class and store it away.
This client is able to perform
multiple requests, and
it will cache connections to
servers being quite efficient.
The client will be used by the get method.
We give a URL as a string and
we expect back the body again as a string.
So, we call client.prepareGet for
the URL, execute,
this gives us back a Future but,
not a Scala Future which we call get.
And this will wait until
the response is there, so
we have the response here to deal with.
Then we check the res, return status code.
If it is not an error code,
then we look at the first 128
kilobytes of the body and give that back.
Otherwise, we reply with a BadStatus.
And the reply in a synchronous
method like this one,
of a bad result, is done by
throwing an exception as we know.
This looks very simple, but
it is also problematic.
The problem is precisely here.
Here we block until the web
server has replied and
given us the whole body, and
we have stored it in memory.
If we, for example, use this method from
an actor, then this actor will be blocked,
it will not be able to execute
anything else until this finishes.
Which means that during this time
the actor is deaf to other request.
For example, we will not be able to send
it a request to cancel the operation.
The problem is that blocking in
this fashion wastes one thread,
on our machine, and in the virtual machine
you can have a few thousand threads,
but for
sure you cannot have millions of them.
And you have millions of actors.
So there is a mismatch and
we should always think that we should not
waste threads because they
are a finite resource.
How do we fix this?
Well, we still use the same client, and
as the name implies, it is an async
http client so it is capable of performing
the operations in non-blocking fashion.
First, we do the same thing,
but we stop at the execute.
This gives us back a Future.
We want to adapt this into a Scala Future,
so
we construct a Promise,
as you have seen two weeks ago.
The Future returned by AsyncHttpClient
is not a java.util.concurrent Future,
it has some added functionality.
Namely that you can add a listener.
When this Future is completed,
this listener which we register
a runnable on, will be run.
So this gets executed.
So when we call f.get in this code,
it will not block because we
know that it has been completed.
Running this runnable,
will need an executor,
because it is a task which is to be run
asynchronously and that is a common theme,
theme that you will need a thread poll in
the end on which to execute these tasks.
In the end we need to return a Future and
you get the Future from
the promise by saying p.future.
AsyncHttpClient is a Java library
using Java and its own Futures.
So what we have done here is
in essence a mapping from
the listenable Future of HttpClient,
to Scala's Futures.
I have included this here to
demonstrate a common pattern.
If you have an event based source for
something and you want to wait for
a single shot event, like in this case,
it is best to wrap things in a Future.
And expose that as an API.
Then, if someone needs
a synchronous version,
they can still await if
they really need to, but
being asynchronous as the default
is good for reactive Applications.
That was the main lesson
to be learned here.
A reactive application needs
to be non-blocking and
event-driven from top to bottom.
If there is one blocking piece in it,
it will infect all other
code which tries to call it.
Therefore watch out and try to use
asynchronous libraries where possible.
Now that we have the ability to
retrieve documents from the web,
we just need to find the links in them.
This entails parsing the HTML of
the body strings that we have here.
And for that purpose we use
a Java library called Jsoup,
which we use from this artifact and
import here.
Parsing a string of html
text yields a document and
a document is a structured representation
of the html tags which we can query.
In this case we look for
all anchor tags which have an attribute.
We then grab an iterator over the set
of these potential links to visit,
and convert it to a Scala one
using the Java converters utility.
And then this for
expression, for yields for
every link, the absolute URL,
that is contained in the href attribute.
And that is then the iterator of URLs
that gives us the further sites,
further links to visit.
With these preparations,
we can write our first Actor.
This is the Getter,
which gets the URL to visit and
the depth at which this
is currently happening.
The first thing that this Actor needs to
do is go to web, using the web client,
and fetch the url.
This gives us back a Future
as we have programmed, and
when this Future completes it can
either be successful or a failure.
In order to make the Actor aware of this,
we need to send it a message,
that's all Actors do.
So in case of a success we retrieve
the body stream that we obtained and
send it to this Actor for
further processing.
If it is a failure,
we also send it to this Actor,
wrapped as a status failure message.
This pattern Is so
common that Akka includes it as the so
called pipeTo pattern.
When you import Akka to put under pipe,
you can say future.pipeTo and
then some actor ref,
usually the self address of the actor.
But we know using Scala syntax,
we can make this even a bit more nice.
By removing the dots and the parenthesis,
and then this reads like normal english.
WebClient get url pipeTo self.
It's a recipe for
what this Actor does in the beginning.
Within this, we have two steps that
are eh, executed asynchronously.
The get needs an executor and the pipeTo
needs an execution context to run
a Java ListenableFuture and
a Scala concurrent Future respectively.
These execution mechanisms are picked
up implicitly from the surroundings
which we provide here by saying
implicit val exec which is
an executor and an execution context.
And it just so
happens that the context.dispatcher so
the machinery that runs the actor
itself can also execute Futures,
both Java Futures and Scala Futures.
So this implicit value here is used in
both places to make the Futures run.
Now that we have arranged for
the data to arrive at the actor,
we need to write down it's behavior,
what shall happen in this case.
If we get a string, which is the body,
then we use our find links method,
to get an iterator of all the links and
for each of those links we
send them in the message.
Context has another nice
method which is called parent.
Remember that every Actor was
created by exactly one other Actor,
and that is its parent.
We can access it like so,
which gives us an Actor if.
Then we send the message to
check the new link we found at
the depth which we have been told.
Once we have communicated all
the links back to our parent,
we stop which means sending the parent
a done message and stopping ourselves.
In case of a failure we just send
the Done right away and stop.
What we have learned here is that
actors are run by a dispatcher
which is potentially shared
among multiple actors and
this dispatcher is also
capable of running Futures.
The next actor which we'll,
we'll be writing is the controller.
And in that one, we would like to
log the progress which is made.
Logging is also something
which is handled by Akka.
There are many flavors to solve
this particular problem and
many frameworks out there.
This, the solution which we chose
is specific to actors in the sense
that it is focusing on not blocking
the entity which wants to do the logging.
The obvious way to achieve this is not to
perform any IO like writing to the disk or
to the network directly, but
to pass that off as a task to a dedicated
actor because we know that sending to
an actor is a non logging operation.
You can set the overall log level
with the setting akka.loglevel.
I put it to debug in this example.
You can conveniently use the logging
by extending the actor trait with
ActorLogging which will give a log Method,
that returns the logger for this actor.
The source information provided by this
logger will contain the actor's name.
So there you have a case why
it is very important that you
properly name your actors.
Here we simply log a debug statement that
we received a certain message given here.
There is a very simple
syntax using this pair of
braces to denote something
which needs to be put in.
Without further ado, we will look
at what the controller now does.
Remember?
The job of it was to accept that
check messages for certain URLs,
and once everything is done,
to send back the overall result.
The result needs to be collected
somewhere, an this is the cache here.
Which is a set of strings, and the strings
will be the links which were visited.
Whenever a check request arrives, we log
it at debug level to see the progress.
Then, if the cache
already contains the url,
we don't need to do anything about it.
Or if the maximum depth is 0,
But otherwise,
we need to create a new Getter.
Tell it about the URL to fetch and
decreasing the depth by 1.
This is created using actor of
which gives back the actor if, and
we need to keep track of all
the children we have created.
This is kept in the second
set named children up here,
which is a set of ActorRefs.
Finally, this url will have been visited,
so we add it to the cache.
The Getter which we have just
created will go to the web client,
ask it, retrieve the documents,
get back the links and we'll send
other check requests at depths minus one,
because that's what we taught it to do.
And at some point, it will be finished,
and then it will send a Getter.Done.
At this point we remove it
from the children's set, and
once no getter is running anymore we
know that the whole process is finished.
So we tell our parents the result.
The result is just the set of links
which we have encountered here.
At this point, it is important to note,
that we are sharing the cache here.
If we would have used a var cache
with a mutable set instead,
then sending that to the parent
could have disastrous effects.
For example,
this controller might be used to
process another query keeping the cache,
would be a valid use case.
But then the result which had been
sent back to the parent points to
the same set which is
mutated by this actor and
then the other actor will be confused
as to what the contents of the set are.
It is much better to prefer
using variables here
which point to immutable data structures.
This way, they can safely be shared as
is done here, and that is the third
point which we have encountered on our
journey, the third lesson we learned.
The controller and getter,
which we have written so far,
play well together as long as the web
client always yields a result.
But what if, for example, a web server
takes really long to respond or
does not respond ever?
For this we need to foresee a time out.
A simple possibility is to us another
function of the actors context.
A capability to set a receive time out.
This receive time out is
a timer which is reset, or
restarted, after the processing
of each message.
So, whether we get a check or
a Getter.Done or even this ReceiveTimeout.
Once we have processed it,
the ReceiveTimeout will be reset again,
to ten seconds.
When it expires, we get namely
this ReceiveTimeout object here.
And in this case,
we tell all our children to abort.
Of course, we need to code this
functionality in the getter as well.
Then we can see here, we add a new case.
Case abort in which we just stop.
In order to support services
like the receive timeout,
Akka includes a basic scheduler.
The focus of this scheduler implementation
is on supporting a very high frequency
of scheduled tasks, but
also very frequent cancellation of these.
The flip side of this is that
it is not terribly precise.
It's main use is to schedule
the sending of a message to an actor
at a future point in time,
which is the first variant given here.
The object which is returned from schedule
once, is a cancellable which can,
which you can use to cancel the task.
But be aware that there might be a risk
condition between the task firing and
you cancelling.
So it is possible to receive
the message in the target actor
after cancel has been called.
This is usually not very problematic,
because often it is the Actor itself
which schedules the message
it wants to receive later.
And then the Actor can just store away the
knowledge that it has cancelled the task,
and can then ignore the message
should it arrive the nonetheless.
There are two other variants,
this one more for scholar, and
this one more for Java.
For running an arbitrary block
of code after the delay.
But these two methods
should be used with care.
We could have implemented
a timeout in a different fashion.
For example, if we wanted to have
a timeout which fires ten seconds
after the controller starts and
not not ten seconds
after the last message was processed
then we might use the scheduler.
The context gives you access
also to the whole system.
The system is the container
in which all actors run and
it contains many services among
others also, the scheduler.
And you can ask it to schedule once in
ten seconds that this block of code runs.
Now we say that after these ten seconds we
want to tell all children
that they shall abort.
What is the problem you
see with this code?
Is it that it does not compile or
is it not thread-safe, or
will the scheduled code simply not run?
The right answer is that
it is not thread-safe and
the reason is that the scheduler
will run this code and
it will run outside of
the context of the actor.
It will not be run by the actor.
It will be run by the scheduler.
And this means that there is no
protection that this code might run.
Concurrently with the actor,
processing the next message.
And both of these codes, then,
the actor and this block,
access the shared variable children,
and they try to modify it or
try to read from it, and
that could have unpredictable results
if there is no proper synchronization.
And the trick was,
that actors encapsulate their state
such that no synchronization is needed.
This is plain var and
we don't take any locks.
It would be nice if the compiler
could tell us about this problem, and
give us an error that we
did something wrong here.
That is unfortunately not yet available,
or it would be nice if the actor could
somehow magically know that this code
shall not be executed by the scheduler and
refuse to run it, but
that also is impossible to realize, so
this is why you need to manually make sure
that this problem is not one
which you invite into your code.
So how do we do this properly?
This is why I emphasize most the first
variant of the scheduleOnce method
which takes, besides the delay,
an ActorRef and the message.
And the scheduler then makes sure that the
message is delivered after the delay has
lapsed to the ActorRef and
we get it here in the behavior.
Here we can safely access
the actor's state and
in this case tell all children to abort.
Similar issues can occur if
you mix futures and actors.
As an example, we have here a simple
cache actor which when it gets a request
to get a url if we look into its
cache which is a variable here, and
if it finds something it will
reply with the element in there.
Otherwise, it will have to go to the web
and actually fetch the document.
As we remember, WebClient get url
returns a future which we can use for
each upon to act when
the body has been received.
And in this, that case we just update
the cache and reply to the sender.
The first problem is exactly
like in the scheduler case.
This access to the cache,
which happens from outside of
the actor's scope, namely in the scope
of the callback on the future.
And if the actor runs at the same time,
then both may access the cache
variable and there might be clashes.
Fortunately, we know how to fix this.
So, we take this future, we map it and
pipe the results to ourself.
And this result will contain the body,
the url and
the sender of the original request,
in one package.
And once we get it here we can safely
update the cache and reply to the client.
But this actor contains another problem.
The transformation described by
the map operation on the future,
runs the code which you give it,
in the future.
And that means that the sender
will be accessed in the future.
This is problematic because sender is
giving you the actor ref which corresponds
to the actor which has sent the message
which is currently being processed, but
when the future runs, the actor might
do something completely different.
Therefore, we must cache the sender in
a local value and when you reference
this local value in here and the closure
which is formed by this function literal,
will contain the value itself and
not the recipe of how to obtain it.
So it will not call the sender method.
So the fourth thing we learned is that
we should make sure that we do not
refer to actor state from code
which is running asynchronously.
For example, using the scheduler,
or in the future combinators.
The last actor which we need
to create is the receptionist.
In this implementation the receptionist
always will accept requests, but
it will make sure that only one web
traversal is running at any given time.
Thus, the receptionist
can be in two states.
It can either be idle,
waiting for the next command.
Or a command can also already be running.
When waiting, when we get a request,
we need to start the traversal and
switch to the running state.
In the running state, when we get a
request, we cannot execute it immediately,
so we append it to some queue and
keep running.
When we get back a result
from the controller,
we need to ship that back to the client
and then run the next job if there is one.
If there is none,
then we go back to the waiting state.
In our formulation of the two behaviors,
we will need helper methods.
And the first one is run next whose job
it is to pick the next job and run it.
Here a job is a type of a client,
ActorRef,
which has sent the request, and
the url, which shall be visited.
When the job queue is empty, then there
is nothing for us to do and we go back to
the way things stayed, otherwise,
we need to instantiate a new controller,
send it the work which is to check this
given URL at the head of the queue.
And here I hardcoded the depth
of the search to two.
And then we are in the running
state with this queue.
As always it is a good idea to name
actors, and these are controllers so
we name them C something, but
there is one condition you,
you may remember that actor
names need to be unique.
So we cannot call them
all just controller.
To facilitate that, there is a variable
request number which gets incremented
everytime we execute one next.
That means that during each run of this
method, this number will be unique.
This number could've also be used,
for example, for statistics purposes,
so that you can ask the receptionist how
many requests it has already processed.
The second helper method
is used to enqueue a job.
Give a queue which is a vector of jobs and
a new job.
We simply check if a queue
has a certain size.
We're limited to three here.
Then we immediately reply with a failure
and stay in the current state.
Otherwise, we append it.
Now we can plug all things together,
to show the two behaviors
in their full glory.
First, waiting,
once we get a URL to check,
we become runNext off a queue
with this one job in it.
Eventually, the controller
which was spawned in here,
will send back a result of links.
We look at the queue head to find the job,
extract the client, and
send the result with the links and
the job URL back to it, then we
stop the controller, because we will want
to use a new one for the next request.
The next request is obtained by using
runNext with the tail of the queue.
This might be empty, then we would
go back to the waiting state.
Or their might be something left,
and then we stay here.
If in the running state
a get request is received,
then we simply enqueue the job and
stay running as we said.
During our journey of designing an act,
actor system we have learned how
to do that, but we have also encountered
the following valuable lessons.
First of all, a reactive application
needs to be non-blocking and
event-driven from top to bottom,
meaning that you should strive for
the use of only asynchronous
libraries where possible.
Asynchronous libraries often have use for
an executor or
a thread pool, and we have seen
that the dispatcher which runs
actors is very useful also in that regard.
The third point was to always prefer
immutable data structures because they can
be safely shared, and there is no problem
in sending them across thread boundaries.
The fourth point was to always prefer
context.become to model different states
of actors, and to keep the data local
to the behavior where that makes sense.
I have shown you some examples of
where deviation might be useful.
If in doubt, always code both ways and
compare them, and
choose the one which is more readable,
more clear, or more concise.
And also consult with your colleagues,
who will have to maintain that code.
And the fifth and very important lesson
is, do not leak the actor's internal state
to code which runs asynchronously, because
that breaks the actor model encapsulation.
We have assembled all the pieces for
our program.
Now we also want to see it in action.
For that, I have created a main actor, as
you have seen before, which will run it.
The first it will do is to create
a receptionist, and then it will send
a request to this receptionist to
check a well known website for links.
The reply will be received here, and
it can either be a positive, in which case
we take the set of links, convert it
to a linear structure from a set,
sort that one and convert it to
a string by saying, results for
this URL, and
then on each line is one link.
If we get the failed result,
we print failed to fetch.
Finally, we want this
application to terminate
if no more messages
are received after ten seconds.
In that case, we get the received
time out and stop the program.
It should be noted that the ACHDP client
in here has some resources which it
needs to shut down for
the JVM to properly terminate.
I have created a run configuration
as before using the main
class akka.main, and if we run it,
we will see the output.
Results for http://www.google.com.
We see a number of links were found.
The search depth was two,
if you remember correctly.
So first it was going to that.
I can tell you I tried it.
This gives you a redirect
to google.com/ and
then some very complicated cookies,
and if you follow that one you
get the actual search page, which you
see in your browser when you open it.
And that contains a lot of links,
some international links.
I have a German set browser and
I'm currently in Switzerland,
so you see here all what is on,
on the front page of Google.
Now let us try to give
the receptionist a bit more work.
You may recall that we limited the queue
it keeps to the depth of three.
Meaning, it will start
processing the first request,
then it will queue these three, and
it should fail on the fourth one.
Running it again,
we see the first failure, here,
fourth request was rejected.
Then we see the result for
the first one, which we already know.
And after that we have the results for
slash one, two, and three.
These are URLs on which there
is nothing to find on Google, so
they turn up just the link,
which we gave initially as visited.
This program is of course
no proper link checker.
You would have to augment
the functionality,
especially in the getter to make it right.
But I'm sure this can serve as
a good starting point if you would
ever choose to implement one.