Hi.
In this video we are going to show you how
to install the tools required for this
class on your machine.
This video is for people using the Linux
operating system.
If you're on a different operating system,
check the Getting
Started section in the video lectures part
of the class website.
Everything that we show in this video is
also
explained in text on the Tools Setup wiki
page
on the class website.
So we go to the Tool Setup page, and we
see that
there are three things that we need to
install for our class.
The first one is the JDK, the Java
Development Kit.
Which is a runtime environment on which
Scala programs are executed.
The second one is SBT, a build tool for
Scala, which
you will also be using for submitting your
assignment solutions to Coursera.
The third one is the Scala IDE for
Eclipse, which
is the IDE we are going to use in this
class.
Okay, so let's get started by installing
the JDK.
In the section installing the JDK there
are three sub-sections for different
operating system.
In this video we are going to look at the
part related to Linux.
While recording this screen cast, I am on
an Ubuntu system, and therefore, these are
the instructions that apply to my system.
If you are using a different Linux
distribution,
you will have to do the JDK installation
differently.
So one of the other things that we need to
do
is start the terminal, and install the
open JDK using apt-get.
To start the terminal I just click on Dash
Home in the window and I search
for terminal.
And I can launch Terminal.
Since we will be using the Terminal a lot
in this tutorial,
I will lock it to the Launcher and make it
available more quickly.
Okay, so the comment to install Open
JDK on Ubuntu is the following sudu
apt-get install openjdk-7-jdk.
And you have to enter your password, and
then apt-get will ask you to confirm.
And now it will download and install the
JDK.
Okay, once that apt-get has finished
installing the JDK, we
want to make sure that everything has been
set up correctly.
We go back to the Tools Setup page, and we
gotta read the section
Verifying Your Setup.
So what you have to do is, start a new
terminal,
so it loads the existing one and start a
new one.
And then you have to type java-version.
Now you should see the version number of
the JDK that you just installed.
Okay, since this worked fine we are
closing the
terminal window and moving on to the
second step.
The second
step is installing SBT.
In order to install SBT, it has to be
downloaded from this URL.
So we simply click the URL, we save the
file and
Firefox will send it to the Download
folder of my Home directory.
So we go to the Home directory, Download
folder, and we see this SBT archive.
So, now we have to extract the archive.
One way to do this in Ubuntu
is right click on the file and just
selecting Extract Here.
Okay.
So the SBT folder that has now been
created contains
bin directory, which in fact, contains the
executable for SBT.
So since SBT is a program that we might
want to use in the
future, I'm going to move it to a
different location.
So I cut the SBT folder and in my Home
directory I create a new folder,
which is which I call Applications.
And I paste the SBT folder in there.
Okay, so let's go back to the Tools Setup
instructions.
So we already unpacked the archive.
And now what we need to do is add in the
bin directory
of the SBT installation that we
just downloaded to the PATH environment
variable.
In order to do that, you have to open.
bashrc, which is in your Home directory in
a text editor.
The easiest way to open that file is to
open a terminal, and type
in gedit.
And then.
bashrc .
This will open the Text Editor with the
bashrc file.
Now in order to add SBT to the path we go
back to the set of instructions wiki page,
and we copy that export command that we
need to add to the bashrc file.
We copy it and we go back to gedit, and we
scroll
down to the end of the file, and just
paste the command.
Now, in fact, you have to update the path
your SBT directory, with the real path on
your system.
So, the place where I installed it is in
/home.
And then my username, luc,
and then /applications, in sbt/bin.
Okay, so I close the gedit text.
I save my changes.
And now I have to verify that the SBT has
been installed correctly.
In order to do that, I have to open a new
terminal window
because the changes to bashrc will not be
applied to existing terminal sessions.
So I close my terminal.
I open a new one.
And in order to test SBT I
type sbt -h.
As expected, I see a help message from
SBT, so everything is fine.
Okay, so now we close the terminal window,
and the last thing
that we need to do is installing the Scala
IDE for Eclipse.
The Scala IDE for Eclipse, with all the
plugins and settings that
we need for the course, can be downloaded
from the following URL.
So I open this page in a new tab.
And I scroll down to the download links.
Now you just have to select the
Eclipse distribution which matches your
operating system.
In my case, I'm on the Linux system with a
32 bits.
So I download this file and save it in the
downloads folder.
Okay, once the download of the Scala IDE
has finished, I can close the Download
window.
Close the Download page for the IDE.
And open the Download folder in my Home
directory.
Next, we unpack the downloaded Scala IDE
package using
the same mechanism as we used before for
SBT.
So, we right click on the file, and we
select Extract Here.
Okay.
Again, since the Scala IDE is an
application that we will continue using
in the future, I right click on the new
Eclipse folder, select Cut,
then I go to my Home folder, and then to
Applications.
I right click and select Paste.
In order to start Eclipse, I simply open
the
Eclipse folder and double click on the
Eclipse execute.
When starting Eclipse, you always have to
define which workspace you are going to
use.
We recommend that you create one workspace
for this class, which you then can reuse
for all the assignments of the class.
Okay, I will do that right now.
So I click the Browse folder to go to my
file system, I go
to my Home folder, and the create a New
Folder, which I call progfunworkspace.
Okay, I select the folder, I click Okay,
and then I start Eclipse.
Okay, so this is the Scala IDE.
In order to verify that everything is
setup
correctly, I go to the setup instructions
wiki page.
On the bottom of the page, there is a
tutorial
on how to create the Hello World program
in Eclipse.
So I glue this right now inside Eclipse.
In order to create a new project, you
select File, New,
Scala Project from the menu, and you give
the project a name.
HelloWorld, and you can finish.
Now, we will create the HelloWorld program
file.
So, you open the HelloWorld project.
We right click on the source folder, and
we select New >Scala Object.
You have to give the object a name, so
will use Hello.
And we will put the object into a package.
In this case, Package greeter.
Okay, now the source project for Hello
World can be again found on the wiki page.
So, we go back to the wiki page, and we
scroll down a bit
to find the source code of the Hello,
World application, we select the code.
Right click and copy.
We go back to Eclipse.
And, we paste the code.
Okay.
Now, when we save the file, you will
notice
that Eclipse already compiled the file.
Since this file defines an executable
application,
you can directly run it inside Eclipse.
The easiest way to do this is right
clicking on
the Hello.scala source file, selecting Run
As > Scala Application.
You will then see the output of the Hello
World program on the bottom of the screen.
Good.
So the last thing that we are going to
show you in this
video is a brand new feature that has been
implemented for the Scala IDE.
The feature is called the Scala worksheet,
and it
gives you a very interactive console to
work with Scala.
In order to create the Scala worksheet you
have to right click on a package, select
New, and then select Scala Worksheet.
You have to give the worksheet a name.
And click Finish.
Okay, I have to make this window a bit
bigger.
Okay.
Every expression that you type into a
worksheet will be evaluated on the fly.
In order to demonstrate that, we go back
to the Tools Setup instructions, we scroll
up to the end and we copy the statements
that are at the end of the screen.
We go back to Eclipse,
and, and we paste this code into the
worksheet.
Okay.
So once its safe to file, Eclipse will
immediately evaluate all the expressions
in the worksheet.
So what it we do here is we define a value
x to be 1.
We define a function increase, which
returns its argument increased by 1.
And we test increase by invoking it, and
we pass the value x into the function.
And you can see
that the result of passing x into increase
is the value 2.
Now you can easily go back in the
worksheet and change some definitions.
For instance, now we change x to be 5.
And once you save the file, the entire
worksheet is reloaded and re-evaluated,
and the resulting value now is 6.