Hi.
In this video we are going to show you how
to install the tools required for our
class on your machine.
This video is for people using Mac OS X.
If you're using a different operating
system, check the Getting
Started section on the Video Lectures part
of the class website.
Everything that is shown in this video is
also explained in
text on the tool setup wiki page on the
class website.
So, let's have a look at this page.
As you can see, there are three things
that you need
to install on your machine in order to
prepare for this class.
The first one is JDK, the Java runtime
environment, which is used to execute
Scala programs.
The second one is SBT, a built tool for
Scala,
which will also use to submit your
assignment solutions to Coursera.
The third one is the Scala ID for Eclipse,
which is
the IDE that we are going to use in this
class.
Okay.
So let's get started by installing the
Java debug kit.
Every section in this tutorial has three
sub sections.
one for each operating system.
Since we are currently on Mac OS 10 we
will
look at how to install the JDK on Mac OS
X.
In fact Mac OS X either comes
with Java preinstalled, or it will install
it automatically for you.
To verify if you already have Java, you
have to open a terminal application.
So, if you open the finder, we go to
the Applications folder, and we open the
Utilities folder.
In Utilities, there is the application
named Terminal.
Since we will be using the Terminal a lot
in this class,
it makes sense to Drag it into your Dock.
Okay, so we can close the Finder right
now.
Open a Terminal.
And now we want to verify if we have Java
installed.
In order to do that, you type Java minus
version into the terminal.
On this version, I don't have Java
installed yet.
So I will get the window which tells me to
open Java, I actually need to install it.
So the only thing you need to do is click
the Install button.
Of course you have to agree to the licence
agreements.
Okay, so once the Java installation has
finished, we
just click OK and we run Java Linux
version again.
Now we see the version number of the Java
installation that has been installed.
Okay, so we close this terminal window and
we
move onto the second word that we need to
install.
The second tool that we need to install is
SBT.
In order to install SBT on your system,
you can either use
home brew package match or, or you can do
a manual installation.
In this video I will do a manual
installation.
So we download SBT from this url.
Once the download has finished we now
begin to find it
in the finder and we double click it to
extract SBT.
Okay so since SBT is an application that
we will reuse
in the future we will move it to a
different location.
So I open it and you find a window.
And in my home folder I create the sub
directory named applications.
[SOUND]
Now I take the extracted SBT folder, and
I move it to my newly-created Applications
folder.
Inside the SBT folder you have a big
subdirectory which contains the executable
files for SBT.
So let's close the finder windows and go
back to the tutorial.
So we downloaded SBT, we unpacked the
archive.
And moved it to
the Applications folder.
And what we need to do last is add in
the bin directory of SBT to the path
environment variable.
In order to do that you have to open the
file.
bash on your score profile which is
located in your home directory.
If the file doesn't exist yet, you will
have to create it.
Okay, so let's open a new terminal window.
And let's check
if the batch profile file already exists.
So we type ls.
bash_profile .
In my case, the file does not exist yet.
But it might very well be that you already
have it.
So, in order to create or edit the file,
we can use
the nano text editor, which is a very
simple common line text editor.
We type nano.
bash_profile and hit enter.
So now we need to add one Export command
to this batch profile file.
We go back to the setup instructions.
We copy the Export command, right click
Copy and go back to the terminal.
And paste it using right-click Paste.
Now in fact, we have to change
the path of our SBT installation to match
the path where we actually extracted SBT.
In that case, this was /users/uc, my
username, /applications And then SBT bit.
Now we can exit the nano text editor using
control-x
and we will save the changes to the file
by control
with y and hitting enter for the file
name.
Okay, now we need to verify if SBT has
been installed correctly.
We close the terminal window and we go
back to the instructions.
In order to verify the SBT installation we
have to start
a new terminal window and we have to type
SBT minus H.
If the installation was successful, then
you will
see the SBT help message appear on the
screen.
Now you have to find the version of
the Scala IDE which matches your operating
system.
In my case, I am on a 64 bit Mac OSX so I
click this link.
[SOUND]
Once the download of the Scala IDE has
finished.
We open the download folder in the Finder.
We unpack the Scala IDE by simply
double-clicking the file.
Since the Scala IDE is an application that
we will resue
in the future, we will also move it to our
Applications folder.
So I open a new window.
I go up to my applications folder, and I
move the eclipse folder into my
applications.
In order to open the Scala ID you
simply go into the eclipse folder and you
double click the eclipse file.
When starting up Eclipse, you have to
define which work space you want to use.
We recommend that you create one work
space, which you
can then reuse for all the assignments of
our class.
I will do this now by clicking the Browse
button and going to my Home folder.
Okay, so now here I will create the new
older
named prog fun word space.
I will select the folder and click Open.
By clicking OK eclipse will start up using
that new work space.
OK in order to test the Scala ID we go
back to the tool set of instructions page.
We can close the download page.
And the tool setup page explains you to
create the simple hello world project in
Scala IDE.
I will show you how to do this now.
So you go to eclipse and in the menu you
select File > New > Scala Project.
You give the project a name, for instance,
Hello World.
Okay, in order to enter the source code
for the
Hello World application We have to create
a new scala object.
So we open the project, and we right click
on the source folder, and select New >
Scala Object.
We give the object a name.
In this case, hello.
And we define in which package the object
is defined.
So we put here the package greeter.
We confirm by clicking finish.
Okay, now the source code for the hello
word
application can be found under tools, set
up instructions.
So we go back to the wiki page and we
scroll down to find the source code that
we need.
We select it, copy it.
Go back to Eclipse.
And just paste
it into the file.
We save the file, and you can notice that
once you
save a file, Eclipse will automatically
compile the entire project for you.
In order to execute the Hello World
appllication You simply have to
right-click on the hello.scala source
file,
select Run As, and select Scala
Application.
You will see the output of the Hello World
program in the e, in the Eclipse console.
The last feature that we are going to show
you, is a brand new feature named the
Scala Worksheet.
In the Scala worksheet, you can type
arbitrary Scala expressions.
And see them evaluated on the fly.
It's a great tool to learn and explore
Scala.
In order to create the worksheet, we
right-click
on the Create Package, we select New Scala
worksheet.
You have to give the worksheet a name, and
click finish to create it.
Okay, I will increase the size of this
window
in order to see all the, all the words.
[NOISE]
Now to try out the worksheet we have
prepared some instructions
for you that you can paste in to this
newly created object.
So if you go back to the set up
instructions,
and scroll down to the bottom of the page,
you
will see a few lines of code that you can
copy and paste back in this freshly
created scholar worksheet.
[NOISE]
Okay.
Once you save the file, eclipse will
automatically evaluate all the lines that
are part
of the worksheet, and show the result of
the evaluation on the right hand side.
In this example, we assign the number one
to the value x.
We define a function increase, which
returns its argument decrease by one.
And we test increase by
invoking it and passing x into the
function.
You can see that an increase of x returns
two.
Now, if you go back in the worksheet and
change the definition of x, for instance,
to be 5.
As soon as we save the file, the whole
buffer will be reevaluated.
And you can see that the result of the
invocation of increase is now 6.