Hi.
In this video we are going to show you how
to
install all the required tools for our
class on your machine.
This video is for Windows users.
If you are on a different operating
system, check the
Getting Started section of the video
lectures on the class website.
Everything that we show on this video is
also described
on the Wiki page Tools Setup on the class
website.
So, we go to the Tools Setup page, and we
see there are three things that we need to
install.
The first one is JDK, the Java Runtime
Environment, which is used to execute
Scala programs.
The second one is SBP.
A built tool for Scala projects, which in
this class,
you will also use to submit your
assignment solutions to Coursera.
The third one is the Scala ID for Eclipse
and the Scala Worskheet.
Which is the ID that we are going to use
during this class.
So, let's get started with the JDK.
So, we checked the JDK section, and there
are three
sub-sections for each operating system so,
we go to Windows.
First of all, we need to download the
JDK installer from this URL from the
Oracle website.
And the first thing you need to do is
accept the license agreement.
And then you can download the JDK
distribution for your architecture.
In my case I am on X64 so, I will download
this file.
Once the download has finished, you
just run the downloaded Execute Double
Installer.
You don't have to change any of the
pre-define settings.
The default options are fine.
The installer will also ask you to install
the Java Runtime Environment.
Again, you can just follow the default
options.
Okay once you've finished you click Close,
and you close the Oracle websites.
You don't need to register.
To finish the JDK installation, you need
to add the bin directory
of the JDK that you just installed to the
path environment variable.
How to do this is described on this
website here.
I will show you how to do these on Windows
7.
You go to the Start menu > Control panel.
And in the search box, you type
Environment Variable.
And then, you get the, the option to edit
the system environment variable.
So, you click there.
And you click on the button Environment
Variables.
In the list of system variables, you
search
for the variable named Path, and you
double-click on it.
To this list of directories, you will now
add the bin directory of the JDK.
So, you go to the Start menu > Computer >
Local Disk > Program Files > Java.
You go to the JDK bin directory, and by
clicking in the location bar we can
copy this path by right-clicking.
We go back to the System Variable window,
and we need to add the semi-colon
and paste with Ctrl+V, the bin directory
of the JDK.
If any shut with OK, and closing all the
dialogs.
You can also close all of the Explorer
windows.
Okay, so, now to test
that the JDK installation is successful,
you have to open a Command Prompt.
The Command Prompt can be found in the
Start
menu either by typing ser, by searching
for Command Prompt.
Or we can just go
to Start > All Programs, and then
Accessories.
And you have the Command Prompt.
So, to check the Java installation you
type Java dash version and
you should see the version number of the
JDK you just installed.
The second step is installing SBT.
Again, we scroll down to the Window
section.
And as you can see we have to download SBT
from this URL.
So, we click here and we round it,
download it installer.
Again we can leave off all the default
options and just hit the Install.
Okay, once SBT is installed we will also
verify that everything is
correctly set up so, we go to Start, and
to the Command Prompt.
And to test SBT we have to type the
following command,
sbt sbt dash version.
And now SBT will download a few
dependencies and libraries.
But this will only happen the first time
you actually run SBT.
After that, it will start up much faster.
Okay, at the end, SBT will show you
it's version number, which is supposed to
be 0.12.0.
Okay, we can
exit the Command Prompt.
Now, the last thing we need to do.
Is installing the Scala IDE for Eclipse.
The Scala IDE for Eclipse can be
downloaded from the following URL.
On this website you just scroll down to
the list of
downloads, and you select the package
according to your operating system.
Once the download has finished, we open
the downloads folder in the Explorer.
You right-click the archive and you select
Extract All.
I'm going to extract the Eclipse, the
Scala ID for Eclipse to my desktop.
Once that Windows has finished extracting
the Zip file, we
will close the Explorer windows and also
the IDE download site.
Now we have to start Eclipse.
So, for that we go to the Desktop, we open
the Eclipse folder.
And we just run the Eclipse Executable.
Now, whenever you start Eclipse, you have
to tell it which workspace to use.
For our class, we recommend that you
create one single
workspace that you can then reuse over all
the assignments.
So, I'm will do that now.
I go to my Home folder.
And I make a new folder which I called
Coursera Workspace.
And I select that as my Eclipse workspace.
Okay, so this is the Scala IDE for
Eclipse.
In order to test whether everything has
been
set up correctly, we go back to the Wiki
page and we create a small Hello World
project
in Eclipse according to steps described on
this page.
I will just do it in Eclipse right now.
So, I maximize the window.
I select File > New >Scala project
and I give it a name.
Hell, hello world.
'Kay.
So, in every Eclipse workspace you can
have multiple projects.
Now in order to create hello world.
programming Scala.
We right-click on the Source folder.
Select New > Scala Object.
And we create the Scala object, which we
call Hello, for instance.
And we usually put Scala code into a
package.
So, we create package which is named
greet, greeter.
Okay.
Now, the actual code for the Hello World
is given on the Tool Setup page.
So, we go back to the Tool Setup page, and
we scroll down to see the source
code and we just copy it and paste it
inside Eclipse.
Okay?
We save the file, and you see when you
save
the file Eclipse will immediately compile
the workspace, the entire project.
Okay once the file has been compiled, we
can run the Hello World program by
right-clicking on the Hello dot Scala
source
file, choosing Run As, and selecting Scala
Application.
You will see the output of the Hello World
program in the Eclipse console.
Okay, this installation of Eclipse also
come with a
brand new feature, which is called the
Scala worksheet.
Creating a Scala worksheet is easy, and
again, described on the Tools Setup Wiki
page.
You can read through the instructions
here.
I will just read right now in Eclipse.
So we right-click on the creator package.
We select New and we choose Scala
Worksheet.
We give the work sheet a name.
Okay?
This will give us a new Scala object
in which we can write new arbitrary Scala
expressions.
And those will be evaluated on the fly.
To get an example, we have some code on
the Tool Setup page
that we can just copy and paste into the
worksheet that we just created.
Okay.
And once you save the file, Eclipse will
evaluate
all the code that is in this worksheet
object.
So, you can see we define a value x to be
one.
We define an Increase function which
returns its argument increased by one.
And then to test it we just invoke the
increase function and
pass x into it, and you see that the
result is two.
You can change a definition, for instance.
Now we say x to be five, and once you save
the
file, the change will be immediately
reflected in the rest of the worksheet.