Hi.
In this video we are going to show you how
to work on the programming assignments.
We show you how to download them, how to
import them into Eclipse,
how to test your code and how to submit
your solutions using SBT.
Okay, so lets get started by going to the
assignments page.
And we open the Getting Started section,
and
we go to the instructions of the example
assignment.
So the first thing you need to do is
installing all the required tools.
How to do this is explained on the Tools
Setup page.
I will quickly show it to you.
And for every operating system, you can
also have screen
task which also shows you how to setup the
tools.
Since I already installed everything on
this
machine, I just go right into the
assignment.
So, the first thing you need to do is
download the assignment archive.
Okay.
We open that file in the Explorer.
And now I will extract the assignment
archive into my home directory.
So I right click, select Extract All, and
I will create a new
directory in my Home folder, which I will
use for the programming assignments.
So I go to my Home directory, I create a
new folder, I call it progfun assignment,
and I click Extract.
So I close the Explorer window and go back
to the assignment.
And the first thing we're going to do is
starting Scala REPL inside the project
that we just created.
How you can do this is explained on the
SBT tutorial website.
So I open the SBT tutorial.
And they follow the instructions which are
on this page.
So, I open a CommandPrompt, I go to the
directory of my assignments over I go see
the
progfun assignments and then here I go see
the example since
I am working on the example assignment and
I start SBT.
Okay, once the SBT console has loaded you
can,
from SBT start, the Scala REPL using the
console command.
So you type console, hit enter, and then
SBT will start the Scala REPL.
Now we are
in the Scala interpreter.
Here we can type arbitrary Scala
expression
and they will be evaluated on the fly.
For example, you can say println, and
parse the string,
and the print align comment will be
evaluated.
That is how we recommend that you start
the Scala interpreter during this lesson.
In order to close the Scala interpreter
and get
back to the SBT console, you have to type
Ctrl+D.
You will not see anything on the screen
except that this Scala interpreter exists.
Now we are back in the SBT shell.
Okay so now we will go back to the
assignment.
We close the SBT tutorial and we move down
to
the next step, which is opening the
project in Eclipse.
So, you start up Eclipse.
In my case, I have a shortcut on my
desktop.
And once you start Eclipse you have to
choose a workspace to work with.
If you already created a workspace for our
class, then you can just use that.
Otherwise you just create a new folder in
your home directory and use that.
So my workspace is a progfun workspace in
my home directory.
[SOUND]
Okay, inside Eclipse you can just import a
project that you extracted in your home
directory.
You do this by going to File, Import and
in the General section you select Existing
Project into Workspace.
You go Next and you browse through
the directory where you unpacked the
assignment.
So we go to progfun assignments and we
accept the example folder, which is the
project directory.
Okay, we click finish.
And now we already have the source code
imported into Eclipse.
So we open up the project, and in the
source folder, source main Scala, in the
package example
you see the file Lists.scala, which is the
file
that you actually have to work on during
this assignment.
Okay, so let's go back to the
instructions.
So, the next assignment that you have
to do is actually implementing the
assignment.
If you actually look at the code, there
are
two functions that need to be implemented,
sum and max.
Both functions are currently defined with
a triple
question mark, which means they are not
yet implemented.
Okay, in this case, I will not do a real
implementation, but just return 0
for both of them which is obviously wrong,
but I don't want to spoil the solution.
So let's go back to the assignment.
The next step is running your code.
There are two ways to run your code.
You can start the Scala REPL and use the
functions
that you just implemented in Eclipse in
the Scala REPL.
For that, we go to the command prompt,
we go back to the Scala REPL by typing
console.
And
now we have another look at the source
code.
So the two functions, that we just
implemented are defined
in our object list, which in fact lives in
package example.
So if you want to use the functions, we
have to either use the full name,
example.list.sum, or we can also import
the members of this object into the REPL.
In order to import it, we just type,
import example.Lists._,
which means everything.
And now the two functions that we defined
are available, so we can try them out.
For instance we can try the sum function
and, type sum of list of 1, 2 and 3.
And we get 0 because obviously our
implementation is not correct.
Okay.
Another way to run your code is using a
main object.
This is explained on the, on the
assignment page and I will not go
into details right now.
The next part of the assignment is writing
tests.
So if you go to eclipse, you see that
there is a second source folder which is
named src/test/scala.
And this directory contains tests for our
code.
In fact, we already give you a test suite
for the lists object.
If you open it up you will see that the
lists test suite is a
whole tutorial on how to use Scala test,
the tool that we are using for testing.
It is really important that you work
through this tutorial because
we will be using testing a lot during all
of our class.
Okay, let's go back to the assignment.
After your finished testing and everything
is correct you can submit your solution.
In order to do that you have to go back to
SBT.
Okay?
So we open the CommandPrompt and we see,
in fact, we are
still in the Scala shell right now, so we
type Ctrl+D, and
we are back in the SBT shell, okay?
Now, to submit your solution, the SBT
shell defines a command, which is named
Submit.
The Submit command takes two arguments.
The first one is your email address.
The one that you used for registering on
Coursera.
The second argument to the submit command
is your submission password.
The submission password is not the
password that you use for logging in.
Instead the submission password can be
obtained at the course website.
So we go to the course website and we
scroll
up, and you have to go to the assignments
page.
On top of the assignment page you see your
username and your submission password.
Again, this is not
your login password.
So we copy the submission password, we go
back to the shell, and we paste it.
And now if you type Enter, your solution
will be packed and uploaded to Coursera.
Finally, in order to see your grade.
Again, you go to the Coursera website.
You go the assignment.
And you look at the assignment that you've
just submitted.
I already have a score, because I
submitted before.
Notice that you can submit the same
assignment as often as you like.
So, if I click on the score.
I will see the feedback that I received
for earlier submissions that I did.
So all the feedback below is for
submissions that I did a few days ago.
But you can also see that there is a new
submission,
which I did just right now, which has not
yet been graded.
Usually grading takes between five and ten
minutes.