Welcome, everybody,
to the Principles of Reactive Programming.
And today, we're going to talk
about monads and effects.
But before we do that,
there are a few disclaimers.
Unfortunately, there's no type checker yet
for PowerPoint, and since we will show
a lot of code fragments,
it might be that there are typos or
bugs in the, in the code fragments,
so don't take these as gospel.
All the code will be available on GitHub,
and
that's what you should try to use
when you try to run this code.
Also, when we say code fragments,
we really mean code fragments, so
we're going to leave out a lot of
declarations to focus on the essence.
Again, the running code is on GitHub.
We're using a particular version
of RxScala 0.23 or higher.
And notice that the Scala names can
be different from the RxJava names.
So if you look at the RxJava documentation
and in particular at the Marble diagrams,
sometimes the names might change,
and the reason is that we wanted
to make the library feel natural for
Scala programmers.
And the last thing, the last
disclaimer is that when I say monad,
I do fast and loose reasoning.
In particular,
I don't care about the monad laws.
So unlike, you know, a real monad where
you make sure that the monad laws hold,
I just mean it's a type that has
a constructor and a flatMap.
So with those out of the way,
let's get started.
And what we're going to do in
this first set of lectures is,
we're going to talk about the four
essential effects in programming.
And the four essential effects in
programming are in this table here,
is the one that we're all familiar with,
is synchronous computations
that return a single value.
Then we have asynchronous computations
So, that's the first column.
And then we will move on to
synchronous computations that return
many values and asynchronous
computations that return many values.
But first, we're going to focus
on the leftmost quadrant,
there, synchronous computations
that return one value.
And this is the, the kind of effect
that we're all familiar with.
And this is the effect that's implicit
in most of our programming languages.
So let's look at some code here.
And what we're going to do is we're going
to program a super simple adventure game.
So here, you see the trait Adventure.
And what you can do when you're
running this adventure game,
you can collect coins.
And that returns a list of coins.
And once you have a list of coins,
you can buy treasure.
That's great.
So let's write a little script for
our game.
So we first call the constructor, and
there's also an object Adventure
that contains the constructor.
Then we collect some coins,
and then hopefully,
we collect a lot of coins so
we can buy some treasure.
Now, this program looks very innocent, but
it's really not as innocent as you think.
Because, as in any video game,
actions may fail.
For example,
while you're trying to collect coins,
you can be eaten by a monster, and
then the game over exception is thrown,
and you won't receive a list of gold.
Now, if you look at that script there,
you know, it doesn't show anywhere
that anything can go wrong.
And even if you have successfully
collected all your coins without any
exceptions, you can still get an exception
when you're trying to buy coins, because
maybe you didn't collect enough coins.
And oops, you know,
an exception is thrown.
So the problem is that when we look
at the signatures of collectCoins and
buyTreasure, is that these types don't
tell us that things can go wrong.
And when we look at the sequential
composition of our code,
it doesn't tell us what's
really happening there.
So you collect coins, and
that call will block until
collectCoins has returned
with no exceptions.
And then we execute buyTreasure,
which will also block until
all the treasures are bought,
until this function returns, and
only continues if there's no exception.
So what we really need to do to
make the types honest is that
we want to expose in the type
the fact that things can go wrong.
So instead of having a function from T
to S, we want to have a function from T
to Try of S, where now in the type we
can see that this function might fail.
And how is this function Try defined?
Well, that is in the next lecture.
See you in a bit.