Welcome back to the lecture on Monads and
Effects.
And where we ended up
was with the desire to
make the type of a function
from T to S more precise by ex,
you know, expressing in the type
that this function could fail.
And we used a type constructor Try
to indicate the fact that
this function could fail.
And we didn't say how this Try
was defined, but here it is.
So if you look at the class Try,
it's an abstract class with two subtypes.
And there's one case for success and
the other case for failure.
So you see there the two case classes.
Success takes a value of type T and
extends Try of T.
And the class Failure takes
an exception and also extends Try of T.
So as you see that this type
is like a union type that
expresses the fact that
the function that returns a value
of Try of T can either successfully
return a value of type T or
fail with an exception of type Throwable.
When we adapt our types of
our adventure game with Try,
we will see now that collectCoins,
instead of returning a List of Coins,
will return a Try of List of Coins.
And similarly, buyTreasure will
take a List of Coins still,
but it will return a Try of Treasure.
Okay?
And so again, this Try means it
either returns a list of coins or
throws an exception.
And the same if you return a Try
of Treasure, it means either it
successfully returns a Treasure or
it throws an exception.
Now, however,
our code becomes really ugly,
when we want to compose collectCoins and
buyTreasure.
So let's look at the code here.
Again, we still call the constructor.
But now, when we call collectCoins,
we get a Try of List of Coins.
But notice that buyTreasure
takes a List of Coins,
but we have in our hands
a Try of List of Coins.
So what we have to do is we
are forced to use pattern matching,
and when the call to
collect coins succeeded,
then we can take out the list of coins and
call buyTreasure.
And then when it fails,
we just propagate the exception.
But you see,
this nice sequential composition of code
is now all spoiled, because there
is now pattern matching and so
on and it doesn't look that nice anymore.
Fortunately, there's a couple of
higher-order functions defined on Try
on the Try type.
And for example, there's flatMap,
there's map, there's filter.
And what we will do is we'll use
these higher order functions, and
in particular, the first one, flatMap,
to make this code look beautiful again.
But first of all,
the fact that we have here flatMap and
that we have a constructor for
Try means that Try is a monad,
and in particular,
it's a monad that handles exceptions.
And the fact that it's a monad,
the fact that it has a flatMap,
will allow us to kind of, you know,
guide us toward the happy path.
Because the flatMap takes care
of all the pattern matching and
propagating exceptions such that we only
have to think about the happy part, okay?
So monads are type
constructors that help you
to take the happy path, and
you can forget about the exceptional case.
So let's do some noise reduction here.
So we still call our constructor.
And now what we do is,
we say, collectCoins.
And then we flatMap
the function buyTreasure coins.
And the flatMap will unwrap the Try of T,
and if it's success,
it will give us the coins,
such that we can call buyTreasure.
And if we flip back two slides,
you see that the type of flatMap
is exactly what we need.
It's defined on Try of T, so the,
the, the this pointer is a Try of T.
Then we get a function from T to Try of S,
and then the result is Try of S.
So the types in this code all work out.
All right?
So flatMap is the plumber that
guides you through the happy path.
Of course, instead of flatMap in Scala,
we can also use comprehension syntax
that makes it even look nicer, so
we can write using for comprehensions.
We can say collectCoins and
then put that into coins.
You see the, instead of equal sign,
we use the left arrow, because on the, on
this side, it's a Try of List of Coins and
on the other side it's a List of Coins.
And the same for treasure, and
then we yield the treasure.
So this is a nicer notation for
these monadic functions.
Now let's look at a couple of these
higher-order functions that are defined
on Try of T and
see if we can define them ourselves.
Here's map.
Map takes a function from T to S and
returns a Try of S.
And we have to be,
a little bit careful here
because when we get a value of this,
we have to check whether it was Success.
If it's Failure, we just create Failure.
But notice that calling the function
f might throw an exception as well.
So we have to guard that call in order
to kind of return the right value,
and that's what you see in
the Try constructor there.
It will do a try catch such that the
exception that might happen when you call
f won't escape.
All right.
That was the end of our Try monad and
next we'll go and talk about more effects.