Hey, welcome back.
And we are now going to kind of look
at our next effect, and that's latency.
Remember that in the previous lessons
we looked at exceptions as an effect.
So we wanted to kind of enhance our types,
to reflect the fact that
a computation could fail.
But there's another effect
that we want to make visible,
namely the fact that
computation can take time.
And that's what going, is going to bring
us from the top left to the bottom left.
So, we're now going to go from Try of T
and we're going to introduce Future of T
as a monad that captures the fact
that computations take time.
All right,
let's go back to our simple adventure game
where we had to collect coins and
buy treasure.
And then we had this kind of little script
where we first collected some coins, and
then we bought treasure.
So what we're going to do
is we're going to morph
this little adventure game
into a networking script.
And it's really easy.
So, first of all, we're going to,
kind of, you know, turn our
adventure into a socket, and
instead of collecting lists of coins,
we're going to read from
memory an array of bytes.
And instead of buying treasures,
given a list of coins,
we're going to send a packet
from the US to Europe and back.
All right?
But you see that the signatures
are the have the same shape
as our little adventure game, and
our little scripts even looks the same.
We're first creating a socket,
we're reading from memory,
we get an array of bytes, and then we
send the packet to Europe and back.
Hah, by now you know that
while that this code looks easy,
it's not as easy as you think.
And the reason is that reading
from memory takes a lot of time,
and sending a package from Europe and
back takes even more time.
But this time it's, you know,
expressed in nanoseconds or
microseconds, which is not,
kind of, intuitive for humans.
So let's look at kind of a little
table that tells us the time
that various operations take, you know,
on account of, you know, computer,
and note that these times, you know,
will vary because computers are changing,
so take this as a rough guess, all right?
So taking, you know a typical instruction
1 nanosecond, but let's look at this,
we are, we are going to read from memory,
so that's 250,000 nanoseconds.
And sending a packet from the US to
Europe takes about 150 milliseconds.
And notice that a lot of these times
are limited by the speed of light so
we cannot do much about them.
Now, I don't know about you,
but for me, I have no clue
what 150 milliseconds means or
what 1 nanosecond means.
So let's take these numbers and
take 1 nanosecond and turn that into
seconds and then we kind of calculate
weeks, months, and years from that.
All right?
Because this thing doesn't still,
they say oh, you know,
read from memory takes 50,000 nanoseconds.
Who cares?
All right?
So let's kind of change these numbers
into something that we, as humans,
can understand.
Okay?
So 1 nanosecond becomes 1 second, and
then we'll turn that into days and hours.
Now we get much better picture.
So, in terms of human time scales,
reading 1 megabyte from memory
takes about, 3 days, okay.
So it's like sending, you know,
your kids to do some groceries, and
it takes three days, you know, they have
to go on their horse to the next village,
get the, the groceries and come back.
And of course this can still fail, so when
you're kind of, you know, driving your
horse to the next village there might
be bandits that you know, attack you.
So it doesn't only take time,
it can also fail.
But we dealt with failure
In the previous lectures.
But this one is even worse.
If you look at the sending of
packets from US to Europe and back,
in human times that takes 5 years, okay.
So underneath that simple program
was hidden some enormous latencies,
some enormous time that
this computation took.
And that was not visible in the time so
let's make that, again,
visible in the time.
Because, you know, we don't want this
reading from memory to block for
3 years and then, or it's for
3 days, sorry, and then, you know,
sending the packet to Europe and
back will block for 5 years, and
only continue when there's no exception.
If you look at, in real life,
when we communicate with people,
imagine that you would ask
a question to a person, and
it would take five years,
before you get an answer.
You're not going to wait five years.
What would you do?
Well, what I would do is I would give
this person a self-addressed letter,
I would say here's a question.
I know it takes 5 years for
you to answer it.
Once you have the answer, you just
put the answer in this envelope and
you send it back to me.
That idea in computer
science is called a callback.
And that's exactly,
the mechanism we're going to use.
So if a computation takes a lot of time,
we're going to introduce a type
where you can register a callback
that will be invoked once
this computation terminates.
And again, that computation
might terminate successfully, or
with an exception.
But let's first show that we, as humans,
are still superior to machines.
There's now a lot of talk about, you know,
the rise of AI and that you know,
we have to really scared of computers.
But I don't think that's that bad.
Because apparently somebody has swam from
Europe to the US and that kind of,
you know, took about 3 months.
And if you want to walk
across the continental US,
that takes about 12 months.
So if you cannot make the same journey
that that packet makes, you know,
it means that humans are still
twice as fast as computers,
so I, I wouldn't worry too much for
the machines to take over.
All right?
But here's the question.
Is there a monad that we can use to,
express the fact that
computations take time?
Well, after the break!