All right.
Welcome back.
We just saw that in the simple program
where we were kind of reading some stuff
from memory, sending that as a packet
over to the app from the US to Europe
that there was an enormous latency
involved with that, all right?
And what we asked
ourselves is can we invent
a monad to make this visible,
to make the fact that there's
latency visible in the type.
Just like we did, with the try
monad that made the effect that,
errors could happen explicit in the type,
and the answer, fortunately is yes,
and the monads that we
will use is called future.
The Future of T is a monad that
handles both exceptions and latency.
All right, because still these
computations can fail, but
also they take time.
So this monad really gives you both.
Now let's look at how this looks like.
Well here's the declaration
of the trait Future and
the the single method of course
there's a lot of helper methods there.
But the most important method is
the uncomplete, which takes a callback
that is a function of Try of T to unit,
all right?
And what that means is this,
is this function that I talked about,
this self addressed envelope.
So when you want, when you have a Future,
when you have a computation that can
take a long time,
what you do is you give it a callback, and
that callback will,
when the function when that computation
terminate will call you,
call you back with the result.
And that result can either
be a regular value,
successful value or
a exception, all right?
So that's where we see our good
friend Try of T come back.
And, and
if you look at the scala definitions again
the types might be a little bit more
complicated, but this, this the essence.
And in particular, future stake
the implicit execution context,
you will see that this grayed out for
now we will ignore that
in a couple of lessons from now we will
talk a little bit more about that.
But for now You just import
execution context put in
place is global and
you don't have to worry about that, okay.
Now here's a little bit of
a design question here is
once you have a a function that
takes a call back of that form.
So, if call back that has type try
T of T to unit, it means that,
that function internally probably
will do better formatting or
it will use some of the culminators the
higher, or the functions defiant on try.
But in many cases you will
do a better match to check
whether your computation succeeded,
then you do one thing or
when your computation failed and
then you do another thing.
So, this design of future is
not the only possible design.
For example, what we can do is we
can take the functions there on
the right hand side of that pattern
match and onNext and onError and
pass those separately into
the onComplete call back.
Or what we can do is say oh there's two
functions there let's put them in, in, a,
a type themselves and pass that.
So that's you get that what
that would look like okay,
where we only focus on the essence.
So the first one here would be that
onComplete would take two call backs,
one when the function successfully
completes and one when it fails.
If you're a JavaScript programmer you will
see that JavaScript Often uses this model.
So a lot of javascript based,
APIs that deal
with asynchrony will pick two call backs,
one success continuation, or
sometimes these call backs are also called
continuations, so what you will see is
that they will take a success continuation
which is a function from T to unit.
And a failure continuation which is
the one that takes the exception and
also returns unit.
But of course, what we can also do is
we can package up these two functions
into its own type and
then pass an instance of that type.
So that would be the more O,
O approach to this.
And I'm showing you these alternatives
because, you know many languages,
many libraries all have their approaches
to dealing with Futures in one way or
another, and it's good to kind of,
to see that they're kind of all the same.
Really the essence is that you provide
a callback that will be invoked
once the computation has a highlight and
see has terminated.
Alright, so let's,
given this type of Future of T,
let's adapt our types to show
that reading from memory,
and especially sending packets from
the US to Europe can take a long time.
So now the signatures reach for
memory gets a future
of array of bytes meaning this will be
a computation that takes a long time.
So we have to provide a call back to that,
and
then send to Europe as the same thing,
it returns a future of array of bytes.
But, Future of course, has a,
a lot of higher order functions defined on
it because, otherwise, we would get stuck
in writing ugly code like this or
even kind of stuck, at all, like, here.
We first, read, from memory so, what we
get back is a Future of array of bytes.
And what can we do with the future?
Well we can call onComplete,
where we have to give it a call back.
But now the thing is that what
happens when we get a failure,
because the onComplete must, you know,
what, what, what do we do there?
So this kind of is a little
bit unfortunate, this code.
So what do we do?
Well what we can do here is we can kind
of, you know, refactor it a little bit,
and we say when we are onComplete
we call the packet sent to Europe.
When we do fail,
yeah It's still, not you see,
it's like better matching and
lots of nesting.
So what are we going to do now?
What is our friend?
What's coming to the rescue?
That's flat map.
All right, so we have now a monad,
a type constructor that allows us to
express the fact that computations
take time, and that they can fail.
So let's use this type
constructor Future and,
to make our types more precise.
So here was our Socket class,
readFromMemory,
sendToEurope and now instead of
directly returning array of bytes,
readFromMemory will return
a Future of array of bytes.
And now you can look at this type and you
can see this computation will take a long
time, so it will return a Future and
what do I do with this Future?
I give it a call back that will be
called once my future completes,
either with an exception,
or with a regular value.
And similarly, for
send a packet from the US to Europe,
which took a really long time.
So, there, also, the type becomes
a future of array of bytes.
Now, and just like with Try of T
the code becomes quite messy because,
we can first you know,
calling read from memory is easy because
we get a Future of array of bytes and,
but know what do we do, we now have to
kind of you know, do back at unComplete.
And but unComplete, took a callback,
you know that took a Try of T to unit.
But what we want is we want to have a
confirmation that it is a Future of array
of bytes.
So this is kind of problematic right?
We cannot write it like this because
the right hand side here, it will be of
type unit where as what we want
is a Future of array of bytes.
So there we see that
the compiler is complaining.
It's, there's red squigglies.
You never want to see your red squigglies
in your codes but what can we do?
So, let's try to refactor this
goal a little bit such that
we can return a Future of array of bytes.
So let's, you know, again,
we read from memory, and
then we say when the packet complete,
we give it a callback.
We get the confirmation, but now this
confirmation of the right type is nested
inside the, this complete, so our our,
this is the problem with callbacks.
Your code gets all tangled inside out.
And that's not very handy, but
let's push this to the next lecture
when we're going to talk about
the higher order functions on Future and
let's just look like a little bit
more about how we can
construct Futures and so on.
So here's how you construct a Future.
A Future takes a body, a computation and
here you see this by name function,
you know, arrow T and
it takes an implicit execution context and
then returns a future.
And again, don't worry about
execution context because we
are importing the implicit
global execution context.
But what this constructor does
is it starts an asynchronous
computation and
immediately it returns a future that,
you know, you can register a callback
with when the Future completes.
Now what is important to
notice Is that you can,
of course,
supply several callbacks to that Future.
And the behavior of a Future is that
this callback is called at most once,
because the computation might never
terminate, but when it terminates,
it's called exactly once with the value,
all right.
And if the computation has
already terminated and
you're adding a new callback,
debt callback will be called immediately.
So here's a small example you know,
we are creating three email messages,
and then we're reading from memory, and
future array of bytes, and
this is defined as follows.
We kind of, you know, take the email
from the queue we serialize it and
then we, return the binary, message.
So this is the, the read from memory.
But, but now notice that,
you know, whenever I can, you know,
put a callback to this read from memory,
The code in that body will
be executed only once.
So it's not that when you register two
callbacks that two emails will be read,
all right.
So that's important, so here's a body with
side effects, but for every callback,
the side effect will have been only once.
So this is a very important
thing with a Future.
All right, thank you so much and
see you in the next lecture
when we're going to talk about
higher order functions on Futures.