Welcome back to,
our discussion about futures.
And I left you a little bit in the dark,
the last time when
I showed you how to, you know,
express reading from memory.
Followed by sending the packets from
the US and Europe back, with futures.
And I don't know if you remember but
our code looked a little bit like a mesh,
where we couldn't you know,
get everything to wire up together.
But fortunately, futures have a,
a lot of higher order
operators defined on them.
And, and you will recognize the same
higher order operators that we
saw on try and that we see on list.
And that we see, many, many times,
everywhere, such as filter, flatMap.
And then of course, there are certain
domain specific operators
that are only defined on future,
and that one is recoverWith.
And recoverWith there, you see,
takes a partial function that takes
a throwable and returns a future.
All right?
And there we have, our friends,
the future constructor.
So now let's see how we can
use this to improve our code.
This is what we were stuck with.
And we read from memory, and then we kind
of, you know, did packet onComplete.
And then, you know, we had the
confirmation of the right type but this,
you know, like all this pattern matching
and nesting, it just looks messy.
This is not codes that looks beautiful and
elegant.
And if we're doing, you know,
functional programming style coding,
one of the main things that we want to
achieve is that the code looks elegant.
This doesn't look elegant,
how can we improve that?
By using flatMap.
So flatMap, again,
will hide all this plumbing and
pattern matching for us, such that we can
write nice, smooth, straight line code.
So, let's use flatMap, and here we go!
What we do is we read from memory.
We get a Future of Array of Bytes.
That's called that packet.
And then we just flatMap over that.
So, flatMap will take a Future
of Array of Bytes and
give us in that function,
p is now of type Array of Bytes.
And now we can send it to Europe, which
would return a Future of Array of Bytes.
And the type of flatMap,
go here, will all work out.
All right, so
I'm pretty sure that you agree that
this code looks messy and
this code looks beautiful.
So again, flatMap comes to the rescue,
all right.
Now, let's, drive in,
dive in a little bit and,
and look kind of, you know,
how packets are sent under the covers.
Again, this is, you know, all, toy code.
And the reason is that we need some
concrete code to, to build some examples.
But this is of course,
not production code.
But let's look here.
Imagine that we have an imaginary
HTTP library that has a constructor,
that given a URL, and the request,
will return a response.
Now, an HTTP library is probably going
to make a call across a network.
So, the result of, calling apply on HTTP,
will be a Future of a Response.
And it runs an HTTP request,
asynchronously.
We don't care.
As long as, given the URL and the Request,
we now get a Future of a Response.
So now how can we implement sent packets
from the US to Europe and back with this?
Well, we first create a URL
to some server in Europe.
We create a Request from the packet.
And then we call that, we call then filter
such that we, they're response is okay.
And then we map their response
back to an Array of Bytes.
Now, this is still not safe in the general
sense because it can still fail,
because maybe, you know, the packet,
the, the network is down.
So this packet will not reach Europe.
So let's try to make this code
more resilient, all right?
So we want to make 100% sure
that when we send the packet,
that it actually reaches
the server in Europe.
One way to do that is why don't we
send this packet kind of twice,
all right, to two different servers.
So here is what we do is we kind of,
you know,
send the packet to
a mail server in Europe.
We send the packet to a mail server
in the US just, you know, to be safe.
And then we zip the confirmations, to get,
you know, the, the, a pair of the,
response from sending
the packet to Europe and
the response from sending
the packet to the US, right?
So now, we should be safe because
we're sending it kind of twice.
But is this any better really?
Well, not because if you remember
what zip does with lists.
Zip, if it takes an empty list and another
list, it will just return the empty list.
So zip will always kind of confirm to
the shortest list that you're zipping.
And the same is true when
you're zipping two futures.
So, in that case, you know the error
case is the empty list and
the success case, is the non empty list.
So when I'm zipping two futures and one
of them fails, the whole zip will fail.
So even though I'm doing a lot of work
to send this packet to both Europe and
back, it doesn't help me because the zip
will fail when one of them fails.
So, all right.
So this is not very resilient.
But there was this this,
these two functions.
Well, the one that I showed you, but
there's another one,
recoverWith and recover.
And you can see that recoverWith
looks a little bit like
flatMap because it takes a function that
takes an exception and returns a Future.
And so it's kind of the,
the error case for flatMap.
And then we have recover which
takes a Throwable and returns a T,
which is kind of the map for
the error case.
So let's see if we can use these
functions to write a more resilient
version of sending packets, all right?
So there was our old version,
we were just going to send it.
What we're going to do now is we're going
to send the packet to Europe first.
When that fails, we use recoverWith, okay.
And then, you know, what we get is we
get the function from throwable to,
Future of t, right?
That's what we need?
So then we just send it to Europe,
and then, sorry, to the US.
And when that fails, we just return
the error message with recover,
and if it succeeds, you know,
we're done, all right.
Now the problem with this code is that,
you know,
we're really trying to
send the packet to Europe.
But when,
when it goes wrong sending it to the US,
we get the error message for the US.
So this code is still not really good, but
it's already much better than
our naive attempt, all right?
But the, the thing here that I want
to focus on is that recover and
recoverWith are like the map and
the flatMap, but then for
the error case of the of the Future,
all right?
So instead of you know, getting the value,
they get the exception but
then the signatures are the same for
the rest.
So there's an error channel and
a regular channel, and
they have the same operators
defined on them, all right.
We're going to revisit this code,
in the next section.
And then we're going to do
a little bit of kicking out, and
trying to do some hipster functional
programming, so see you soon.