Hey, welcome back.
Remember we were trying to make
sending packets resilient to failure.
And we kind of messed around a little
bit with the naive approach,
and then we had a better solution
using recover and recoverWith.
But that was unsatisfactory, because
we returned the wrong error message
in case something did go wrong when
both calls would go wrong, all right?
So what we're going to try to do now
is we're going to write a better
recovery combinator, and
that's called fallbackTo.
And what that tries to
do is it will try to
execute the computation that,
so that's kind of, you know,
if this, or, sorry, it will try to,
this is defined on Future of T, so
what it will do is it will
try to run this future.
When that fails,
it will kind of, you know,
try the fallback future, but
if that fails, it will return the error
that the first failure was.
All right?
So we first try to run the this.
If that succeeds, we're done.
If that fails, we try the fallback.
If that fails, we know that the this
failed, so we return the error message,
the error from that one.
All right.
So, if we had that function,
then we can define sendToSafe as follows.
We first try to send it to Europe.
If that fails, we fall back to
sending the message to the USA.
And then we recover by getting
the europeError message,
because that's what
the fallbackTo gives us, and
then we can kind of, you know,
turn that back into the Byte array.
All right.
So this looks much better.
So this fallbackTo is a very nice
combinator that's very useful.
So how are we going to implement that?
Well, it's surprisingly simple.
You're going to notice it yourself.
When we kind of, you know,
looked at this code here
because instead of getting the US error,
we would just return the Europe error,
and in this case,
that is represented by this.
So fallbackTo is simply defined as
this recoverWith, in that case,
we just can throw away the error message.
And then we try that, and
if that fails, we recover with this.
And this is a future, but we know that
it failed, so everything goes right.
So, look at this code for
a few seconds, and
you have to admit that this is beautiful.
All right, so you try this, if that fails,
you try that, and then, you know,
in the end, you say, okay,
if both fails, then we just return this.
Now the reason we introduced futures
was that we had computations
that took a long time and
we didn't want to block on them,
we didn't want to block, you know,
several years in human time for
a computation to finish.
So that's why we had futures
where we pass a callback.
Now, sometimes, when you're testing code,
you still want to block.
Because, you know, you just want
to print something or whatever.
So, you know,
this code is dangerous to use, but
it's useful for testing cases or
when you're writing small sample scripts.
So there's a special trait here
the Awaitable, and that has,
you know, these two functions
in here that will allow you to
block on a Future with
a kind of timeout duration.
So don't use this in production code.
If you see one of your colleagues use
this while you're doing a code review,
you know, you scream, should scream
bloody murder, you should never use this.
Only in small demos and kind of,
you know, little scripts.
All right?
So for example, what we can do here is,
we can kind of, you know,
read from memory, send the packet back,
we get a confirmation, and
now we want to print the confirmation.
So what we can do is we can say we want to
wait at most two seconds, and now we can,
you know, we get an array of Bytes,
and we can turn that into text.
So you know, you should always,
once you're asynchronous,
you should never ever block, except,
you know, when you're debugging or
doing little scripts, okay?
So promise that to me, never block when
you have an asynchronous computation.
And we will see the same when
we're doing Observables.
There we have a similar mechanism to allow
blocking, but that's only for convenience.
But never use this in production, because
once you block somewhere in this whole
pipeline, you might as well, kind of,
you know, have not used asynchrony.
Okay?
So the reason that you introduced
futures was because there was latency.
As soon as you introduce blocking,
you're destroying all of that.
So promise me one thing.
Don't do that, okay?
You're introducing futures, and
now you're stuck in future-land.
Good.
There's one nice thing here in,
in Scala that I have to show you.
These are the postfix operators.
So when you want to kind of
create a duration for, you know,
a number of seconds or
minutes, if you import
scala.language.postfixOps, then
you can write, you know,
a number followed by minutes, so
it looks very much like units of measure.
So five years, that is 1,826 minutes.
All right, good.
So thank you very much.
This was the lecture on
combinators on futures.
In the exercises, what we will
do in the homework, or the labs,
what we will do is, we will show you
a different design for futures, and
then you will have to implement
your own combinators on those.
So, thank you, and see you next time.