Hey, everybody, welcome back.
I must admit, I'm a little bit addicted
to building combinators over futures.
And the reason for that is that
once we move from the world of,
you know regular types,
T or Try of T into future,
into the world of futures, we cannot
use a regular control flow anymore,
because everything becomes callback-based.
And hence, you know, in order to do that,
we need a lot of higher order functions
to make our programming life easier.
And in this lecture, these two lectures
here, we're going to look at yet another
little combinator on futures, and
we're also going to have some fun.
All right, so this really is just a fun,
fun lecture to show,
show off how good we are as
functional programmers.
'Kay.
Remember this code here where we read from
memory and we used flatMap and so on.
Of course, we can write the same
code using for comprehensions.
Because futures are monads,
they support all
the constraints to use for comprehensions,
so we can write the code as this.
Read a packet from memory, put it in
packet, and then send save the packet.
You get a confirmation and
you yield the conformation, and
the result type is Future
of Array of Bytes.
Now, the thing that we were
trying to do is to make
sending this package resilient to failure.
And we messed around with that.
We defined even a new combinator.
And what I want to do now
is I want to define yet
another combinator to deal with failure.
And the combinator that I want
to introduce is called retry.
It's here on the slide.
And retry takes two parameters,
in a curried way.
So the first is the number of times
that you want to retry a computation.
And the second one is the future that,
you know,
the computation that you want to perform.
Okay, so
retry number of times that block, and
then you will return a future as
soon as that block succeeds or
if it still fails after number of time
tries, then you return the error message.
Okay, now here's a simple
implementation of that.
We can just use recursion.
So if you have run out of number of times,
you immediately fail.
So you just return a future that
represents failure with a new exception
saying, sorry,
I tried n times, didn't work.
What do you do otherwise?
Well, otherwise, you execute the block,
and if the block fails, you fall back to,
huh, the recursive call to number of
times minus 1 with the same block.
So this code, you have to admit,
looks pretty nifty.
It looks very elegant, but
the downside is that it uses recursion.
And some people say that recursion is
the goto of functional programming.
And so they frown upon this,
where there is explicit recursion.
And they say, no, no, no, no.
You have to use higher order
functions that hide the recursion.
So let's see what
the consequences of that are.
So let's do some macho programming but
we will do that after the break.