Hey, welcome back everybody.
I left you with this nasty
cliffhanger where I challenged you
to write a recursion function
that kind of tried to
run a future-based computation
n times without recursion.
Okay?
Now I'm going to show you two possible way
to solve this but of course, you know,
maybe you have come up with your own way,
and you can share that on the forums.
That would be fun.
What I'm going to do is I'm going
to use foldr and fold left.
Those are the kind of, you know,
two power tools in our toolbox.
And whenever we do things with recursion,
it's often nicer to do it with a fold.
Okay?
So let's see what the consequences of this
are, because, you know, maybe using
a fold is not always the correct choice.
Okay, so let's geek out for
a bit and pretend that we
are functional programming hipsters.
I should put on here my you know,
my rimmed glasses and
my tweed coat, but, you know,
I remain hippie in my tie dye.
But what we're going to do is we're
going to use foldRight and foldLeft.
So let's refresh our
memory what these are.
FoldRight takes a List,
in this case List with values a, b, and c.
It takes a neutral element e, and
a function, a combination function, okay?
And this foldRight folds the list
from right to left, okay?
So it starts at the right side of the list
and then takes e and applies f to c and e.
And then it goes one step to the left,
because it's folding from right to left,
and then applies f to b and
the result of c and e.
And then finally, it applies f to a and
the result of folding from the right.
Okay?
So it's easy to remember, it's just like
the northern wind blows from the right,
foldRight folds from the right.
Heh, obvious, huh?
Then if you look at foldLeft,
well, that folds from the left.
So what it does is,
it starts with the neutral element and
it does the combiner function.
And it first combines e with a.
And then combines that with b.
And then combines that with c, all right.
So it kind of, you know,
associates the other way around.
We're going to use both foldLeft and
foldRight to
implement our function
to retry a computation.
And here is the solution.
So what we're going to do is,
well, if we want to use fold, and
in this case we'll start with foldLeft,
if we want to use fold, we need a list.
Well, how do we create a list?
I know,
we can create a list from number of times.
So what we will do is, we will create
a list from one to number of times and
put that into a list.
Then we will map over that list the block.
So now we get a list of n blocks.
And notice that we're kind of putting
that block under a unit arrow,
because we don't want to execute the block
just yet, we want to execute them
one by one, because every time we execute,
it might have side effects, so
we have to be very careful to
delay the execution of the block.
Our neutral element is failed.
So we create a new Future.failed.
And then, what we do is we fold from
the left, starting with failed,
and then our combined combination
function takes a future,
that was the thing on the left,
and the block.
And then we try to run the future ,and if
that fails, we're going to run the block.
Okay, so it looks a little bit puzzling,
but if you think a little bit about it,
retry 3 of block will unfold
to failed recoverWith block,
recoverWith block, recoverWith block.
If you don't believe me,
let's do the derivation here.
So first, we're going to run the list, so
we get, you know, that's the simple thing.
So when we run the list, now we're going
to map the number of attempts over that.
And so now we get a list of n blocks.
And remember,
this is super important to do this here,
because we don't want to
accidentally execute the blocks.
Okay, so we have to build this
little thunk that hides the block.
All right.
And now we're going to fold left and
if you kind of, you know,
do the fold left here, you will see
that this gives us the same result.
So by doing a little bit of substitution,
it should be clear
that the result of this function
is exactly what we want.
All right,
now let's try to do it with foldRight.
There's even more higher order functions,
so in this case again,
we create a list from 1 to n.
We map the block, delayed block,
over that, we create the failure.
But now we're folding from the right,
starting with failed.
But we're not really starting with failed,
we're starting with a function that
is delayed failed,
because we kind of have to kind
of turn this from the other side.
So what you will see is the combination
function now takes a block on the left and
a function that returns
a future on the right, and
we have to return a function
that returns a future.
And how do we do that?
By calling the block and
then falling back to the a.
So here you see that, you know,
everything is reversed, and
when you unfold this,
you will see this here.
So this is like, you know, looks, like,
super cool with lots of
higher order functions.
But to be honest,
I think that in this case,
the recursive solution
was the simplest one.
All right?
So sometimes straight recursion
is the way to go and we should
just leave those higher order functions
to the functional programming hipsters.
Right?
And this is one of the most
important things of functional,
of mastering programing.
You have to know when you use recursion,
you have to know when to use folds,
you have to know when to fold left,
because you saw that, you know,
fold right and fold left, you know,
the code looked quite different, and
in one case we even needed
more higher-order functions.
But this kind of balance,
that is, you know,
as you get more experienced in
writing code in a functional style,
that's what you will learn kind of,
you know, it will become natural to you.
Just like, you know, a soccer player
knows intuitively when to jump and
to head in the ball into the goal.
All right.
Thank you.
This is the end of composing futures.
And what we're going to do next is we're
going to look at some even more advanced
ways to deal with futures.