Welcome back everybody.
We're still talking about futures.
One of my favorite types.
And what we're going to do
now is we're actually going
to get rid of the futures in our types.
Because It's kind of
nice to see try of t and
future of t in the type because that makes
the types more honest and more precise.
Because looking at the type
signature we can now see, oh,
this function might fail or
this function takes a long time.
But the price that we have to pay is yet
we have to write things using flatmap and
higher order functions.
Where sometimes really what we want to
do is we want to write just simple,
old-fashioned control flow.
And Async await is a feature
that allows you to kind of,
you know, go back,
forget about futures and so on.
In the limited context, and
then just write regular imperative code.
So, what we want to do is we want
to make effects implicit again.
But, you know, in a limited scope.
All right?
So we still like on the outside It
still looks like a function that
returns a Future, or
a function that use Try.
But internally we want to
treat it inside our code,
inside our code we want to just treat
it as a regular function from T to S.
Okay?
Now there's a feature here in Scala.
It's called async await.
And what that allows you to do is when
you have a code inside an async block,
then you can use await around something
of type future, and get back a T.
So that's a miracle function here, right?
So this is a function here, this await,
that allows you to get rid of
the future in a magic way.
Also notice that this async here
takes an execution context.
We're going to ignore that but
the magic that we want to use here is
that this allows us to just forget
about the future and
just get the regular value back of type T.
Now async await has become very popular
to do asynchronous programming.
If you get C# it has support for
async await.
JavaScript will have support for
Facebook's hack has support for
async await.
And also the dark language from
Google has support for async await.
So even if you're not using Scala,
this is super useful, knowledge,
because it is a language feature
that will be in any modern language.
Now, this thing comes with
a lot of small print,
the Scala version, and
it might be frustrating when you use this.
There's a lot of small print.
You cannot use it anywhere
in all situations.
You cannot use it with try catch.
You cannot use it with nested functions.
So it's a little bit primitive, but
it's still worthwhile
the trouble in my opinion.
Okay?
You will get, you will be screaming and
crying because of the horrible compiler
error messages this thing has implemented,
you know, using macros and
it will spill all the guts on your screen.
Just bite through it and you will love it.
All right?
Because, in the end, it's worth it.
Your code will be much simpler and
much readable.
But, you have to be patient and
you have to, kind of,
you know, go through some pain.
But, no pain, no gain.
All right?
So let's look at our, retry example and,
and kind of, you know, write that,
using regular imperative control flow and
async await.
So what you see here, up here is that
I have an async block which means
that inside the async block I can use
the await when there is a tuture,
I can get that into a regular result,
okay.
So what I do now is I
just declare a variable,
I've my result type and
then I just go into a loop.
And, as long as the result is failure and
I've not reached the number of times,
I'm going to kind of,
you know, try the result.
If the result succeeds,
then this condition fails.
I fall through and
I return the result, okay?
And there we're using this function
here that takes a future and
returns it into a future of Try
of T to make the try explicit.
So I think this code looks pretty nice,
and
the reason is that I can just a y loop.
Now let's look how we define
filter using async await.
Again, look here, we have the async block.
And what we can do now is
we can await ourselves, so
this was of type future of T.
So when I await that,
I get a value of type T.
And then I just check if p holds,
then I return x, and
otherwise I throw an exception.
Now this looks really,
really simple, because,
you think about filter,
filter is something like a conditional.
A flatMap it's even nicer.
So, I, flatMap takes,
a function that, given a T,
returns a future.
This is the instance method,
so the this is future of T, so
how can I call that function?
Well, to do that, I first have to take
a future of T and turn it into a T.
Ha!
But, magically, if I'm in this
async block, I can use await.
So I just await myself.
Now I get a value of type T.
I call the function,
which returns a, future of T,
but since the await wraps
another future on it,
I have to await that f of x and
everything goes well.
Now look how beautiful and
elegant this code is.
Now in the next lecture,
we will introduce promises,
which is another mechanism
to create futures.
And there filter will look like this.
All right?
And, and don't understand the code, yet,
be, that will be in, in the next lecture.
But, you know, you will see that, you see
immediately that that code is much longer
than this code that uses async await,
and so I prefer the async await version.
So, thank you very much.
Next lecture,
we'll talk about these future things
that we silently introduced here.