Welcome, everybody.
This is the last lecture on futures.
And what we're going to do here is
we're going to look at promises,
which are a way to create futures
where you can set the value,
the result of the future,
from the outside.
Okay, let's, again, look at the code that
I left you with last time,
defining filter on Futures.
So filter takes a predicate,
returns a Future.
And so what we do here is
we create a Promise, and
we'll talk about the signature
of the Promise soon.
But, you know, we create a Promise.
Then what we do is, we're going to
kind of wait for this to terminate.
We do that by giving a callback.
If it fails, well, the thing has failed,
so the Future that we want to return,
p.future down there, we are going
to complete that with a failure.
Okay?
When this succeeds with a value x, now we
have to check whether the predicate holds.
If the predicate holds then we succeed.
So what we do is we complete
the Future with Success, with value x.
And otherwise, we will complete
the Failure with a new Failure exception.
All right?
So here you see that this Promise is
something that has a Future that's,
you see that there on the last line,
p.future, and
it has a way to complete
the Future that I hand out.
And the picture I like to draw for
that, and the picture I want to
you to have in your head is a Promise
is a little bit like a mailbox, okay?
So a mailbox is that, you know,
somebody can put something in the mailbox
and you can wait for the mailbox.
So they've got a little
sign on the mailbox.
That's, you know, the, the signal that
your callback has been processed.
And then somebody, the postman,
puts the mail in your mailbox.
And that's exactly what a Promise is.
It's a little bit like a mutable
variable where one side is a future,
where you get the value
of your callback and
where you can set the mutable
variable on the other side.
And that's maybe the reason I'm
not such a big fan of Promises,
because it's a very imperative concept.
Now let's look at the trait,
so trait Promise.
So a Promise has a Future.
You can complete a Promise
using a Try of T.
And then you can also try to complete it.
And the problem is that you cannot,
you know, it's a,
it's a kind of, it's a mutable
variable that you can assign once.
So if you would try to complete it twice,
bad things will happen.
So you can use tryComplete, and
then it returns a boolean that tells you
whether or not it actually has succeeded.
Okay.
And there is the remember
the trait Future.
And so the thing that you
pass in into complete or
try on complete is actually the value
that get passed to the callback, okay?
So I think this is a very intuitive
picture of what a Promise is.
It's like a single assignment variable
where you get the result via a callback.
Let's show an example of a Future
where we're going to race,
so we're going to define race,
that takes two Futures.
And we want to return a new Future, and
that is the first Future
that will kind of, you know,
successfully or unsuccessfully terminate.
So what do we do?
We create a new Promise,
we register a callback with both
Futures that try to complete the Promise,
and then we return the Promise.
And notice that we, here,
we use tryComplete because we're trying
to complete that same Future twice.
And it's a single assignment
mutable variable.
So you can only if you would use here,
complete one of those two would throw.
So that's why we use here,
try on complete.
Okay, and of course,
there are simple helper functions,
instead of creating a try explicitly,
you can kind of, you know,
complete it with success of a value or
you can complete it with a Failure.
These are simple helper functions.
Let's implement zip using Promises.
So zip takes two futures, and
what it does is, it tries to zip them.
When one of them fails,
the whole thing fails.
When both succeed,
you return the pair with the two values.
And this zip here is
a little bit different,
that instead of returning
a future of pairs,
it will take a function that receives
the two values and returns the result.
And that is, then you don't
have to do pattern matching.
So this, this function could also be
called zipWith or and it could be curried.
But it doesn't really matter
what the signature is,
we're interested in the implementation.
So what do we do?
We allocate a new Promise, a Promise of R,
then we wait for this to complete.
If it fails, then, we,
complete the Promise with the Failure.
If it succeeds, then we look,
what the other Future does.
And then if that completes,
we look at whether that's a failure,
then we attempt the Promise
with the Failure.
If it succeeds,
we now have two values in our hands,
the result of the first Promise, and
the result of the second Promise.
We call the function here, and we're done.
Okay?
Now let's look at how we define zip
using await instead of Promises.
And here you see that this is, again, much
more elegant, because what does zip do,
is we just await both of them,
and then we just apply f.
If any of them fails,
the async block will take care of that.
So this is again, you know, a little
confirmation that I like this async await,
despite all the problems that it has.
Now here's an,
an example of a function that is,
can only, I think, well, it can only,
that its nicest implementation is
just using straight recursion,
no async await, and no promises.
And what this function does is,
it takes a List of Futures and
turns it into a Future of Lists.
And the way it works is it just
goes through that list and
runs all the Futures and
collects the results into a list.
And using pattern matching and
recursion, it's quite easy.
If the List of Futures is empty, well,
we return a Future with an empty list,
because we want to pivot the List and
the Future,
that's what you see in the type, right?
We want to swap List of Future becomes
Future of List, so that's what we do here.
If we have an empty List,
we turn that into a Future.
And otherwise we get a Future
followed by a List of Futures.
And what we do is we call the flatMap
of Future, then we get a value T.
Then we recursively sequence
the rest of the list,
which returns a Future of List,
so we flatMap that again.
And then we return a new Future putting
that first value there on
top of the rest of the list.
Yeah, this is quite elegant and nice.
Now, I warn you, the next slides that
use async await, it's kind of grungy.
So we have to kind of, you know,
allocate a list buffer, do a while loop.
This code is not beautiful.
I'm not proud of this code.
This code looks much more elegant.
Okay?
But, notice, again,
straight recursion wins.
It's the most elegant one.
And using Promises,
I don't even know how to begin.
Okay, so this, this might be something
that you want to try at home but
it's definitely not going
to be as elegant as this.
All right, thank you very much.
We have now reached the end of the left
column of the four essential effects.
So we talked a lot about Try of T,
and we talked even more about futures.
And you see that these
are the effects that make
computations that return
one value explicit.
So Try of T is a computation that
returns one value that might fail.
And Future of T is the monad
that expresses a computation
that might fail and
takes a long time, 'kay?
And what we're going to do next is,
we're going to switch from one to many,
and then we're going to
do the same sequence.
So we'll first look at
synchronous collections, and
then we will go to
asynchronous collections.
But for now, thank you very much,
and then see you next time
when we're going to move from
the left column to the right column.
Bye-bye.