So, in this module we're going to look
at some of the traditional ways to
handle events.
Event handling of course, is something
very old almost as old software itself.
We have already seen one instance where
event handling played an important role,
that was simulation and we are going to
see now another, that's user interfaces.
The traditional way to deal with user
interfaces to handle the events there
is based on what we call
the observer pattern.
We're going to explain what it is, and
we are going to explain what it's good for
and also what some of
it's short comings are.
That will lead us then in the next two
modules to a different way to treat
events in these programs which is
called functional reactive programming,
and where events are essentially
summarized in signals.
The observer pattern is commonly
used when we have some sort of model
that maintains the state of
an application, and we need to have one or
more views that essentially present
the properties of the model in some way.
Variants of the observer pattern
are also called publish/subscribe,
or model/view/controller.
The idea is always that we
have some sort of model which
captures the state of an application, and
we might have one or
more views that present that state,
and there would actually be
a bearing number of views.
So, views can announce themselves
to the model with an operation
which we call subscribe.
And the model will then,
whenever there's a change
publish the fact that is new
information to the views.
If you can then inquire the model
about what the new state is and
change it's presentations.
And because essentially,
views announce themselves as published
there can be more than one view.
So, there could be another that also
publishes subscribes itself and
gets the same published information.
Sometimes in using interfaces,
we have a third component which is
called a controller, which somehow
manages the interactions
between the model and the view.
But the controller in fact, is optional.
So let's see how we could
put this into code.
Here is a trait for publishers, so
it's expected that every publisher would
inherit from that trait to gain
the functionality of a publisher.
What is that functionality?
Well, publishers maintain internally
a set of subscribers which you see here.
Initially that set is empty, so
you can add a new subscriber by calling
the subscribe method of a publisher which
simply announces a given subscriber.
That's another trait
which we will see next.
And it, what it does is it
adds a subscriber to the set.
With a plus, equals.
The dual of subscribe of course is
unsubscribe, so I subscribe I can also
announce it's no longer interested in
published info of that publisher, and then
the implementation of that would simply
remove the subscriber from that set.
And finally,
the publisher has a published methods.
What that does is it simply goes
through all subscriber and invokes for
each subscriber a handler
method that the scrub,
subscriber must provide with
the current publisher it's argument.
So let's see the subscriber next.
Subscribers have a simple all they need
to have is this handler method, and
we pass the publisher that published
new information as a parameter
to that handler.
So let's go back to bank accounts which
we have seen before in the module about
functional programming instate you see
the example of bank account that
we have here again for recall.
So a bank account has deposit and
withdraw methods, and
it maintains a private variable balance.
And of course the deposit method adds some
amount to the balance whereas the withdraw
method's subtracts it.
So what do we need to do to
make bank account a publisher?
I have already given you the extension so
bank account now extends publisher.
What we need to do of course is invoke
publish because otherwise nobody would
ever know about changes
in the bank account.
Where do we do that?
Well, every time we change
the state of the bank account, so
I would propose you put a publish here.
And then put another publish here.
One in this, deposit the and
the other withdraw.
We're almost done.
The one thing missing here is you, well
once, we have published what is a view of
the bank account, a subscriber,
what it's suppose to do?
Probably wants to access a important
details about the bank account.
And probably the most important
one here is the balance.
So right now, there's no way to access the
balance directly because the balance is
a private variable.
So let's add an accessal
method called current balance.
It simply provides the current
state of the variable.
Of course, we could have made balance
simply a public variable but that's not
advisable because that would mean that
everybody could not only read balance, but
also write to it, and I believe a lot of
banks would get very nervous if you could
manipulate the balance of your accounts or
anybody's accounts like that.
So here, you see the complete
picture of bank accounts,
I have added all the things that
I drew by hand to the code here.
Current balance and the two publishers.
So let's add a view to this picture.
The thing I want to do is
define a class Consolidator
that observes a list of bank accounts and
that would always be up to date with the
total balance of all the bank accounts.
So the sum of all the balances
in the observed bank accounts.
Consolidator is a subscriber.
So what this Consolidator does initially
is it subscribes itself to all observed
bank accounts as an initialization action
observed for each subscribe, this.
What it needs to do then is maintain
a variable which is the total and
sum of the balances of
all the bank accounts.
I, I've written here private var
total int equals underscore.
That means that the variable
is initially uninitialized,
that's what the underscore does here.
I initialize it by calling
the compute method.
So what does compute do?
The compute method goes through all
observed bank accounts, take the current
balance of each and takes the sum of these
balances, and stores the result in total.
Compute is also called by the handler
method of the subscriber.
So whenever one of
the bank account changes
compute is invoked again to
recompute the total balance.
Of course, one could envision
more efficient ways to do this,
maybe take the difference of
the balance of this account and
apply that to the total variable.
But for now we are doing
the most straight forward and
simple way even if it's
not the most efficient.
Finally, there's an access and method
again total balance which gives you,
gives you the current state
of the total variable.
So let's observe bank accounts
with a little Scala worksheet.
I've called it observers and
I've put it in the package week
two dot publish subscribe.
Where I assume the bank
account class is also located.
So let's define a couple of bank accounts.
We have a bank account a, bank account b.
And now let's define a consolidator
that takes the two bank accounts and
always maintains the total balance.
So we can, find out what the total balance
is by just calling c.totalBalance.
And of course the total
balance initially is 0.
So let's do something with the accounts.
Let's say we want to deposit
20 the currency units in a.
And we want to find out
what's the total balance now.
[SOUND] And that would give us 20.
Well no big surprise, but
remember the total balance actually
does not by itself always recompute.
So it indeed,
it only gives you the current
variable total in the consolidator.
So the consolidator has updated
itself as you can see there.
Let's do another step, let's deposit 30
units in b and do total balance here.
And we would get 50 as expected.
So let's see how we would evaluate what
we've done with the observer pattern.
There's some good aspects, so
one good thing is that we have views
that are decoupled from the state.
We can have a varying number
of views of a given state,
so that's good, and it was overall
rather simple and intuitive to set up.
But there are also some problematic
parts to this design pattern.
The first one is that we have seen that
all the fundamental operations publish,
subscribe, handle, they return unit as
a result so they must be imperative.
Everything they do has to
be by imperative updates.
The second problematic aspect is that,
in fact, there are quite a few moving
parts that need to be coordinated, so
every subscriber has to announce itself
to the publisher with subscribe.
Then the publisher has to essentially
handle these things in the data structure
the, calls back and forth and so on.
That also makes things more
complicated when you add concurrency.
One particular problem is
if you have a single view
that observes two different models
that get updated both concurrently.
In that case, the two models could call
at the same time, the angle method
of the view which gives us possible raised
conditions that have to be handled.
A fourth disadvantage is that views
are still tightly bound to the state,
that's represented in that model.
Every view update is directly
coupled to the state update.
Once we update the state the view
gets updated immediately.
Sometimes we want to have a looser
asynchronous relationship between a view
and a model.
There was one interesting study
from Adobe from 2008 where they
looked at the code base which
is quite UI centric and
they found that indeed event
handling is a very important part.
About one-third of the code in Adobe's
desktop applications is devoted to
event handling.
And for the meter to code that uses that
event handling is also quite integrate.
So more than that share name maybe
one-half of all the bugs in the code.
Where related to event handling.
So that shows that the conditional
ways of doing events by workable and
standard quite an industry
standard right now.
It's far from being perfect, it's quite
bulky and it causes a lot of bugs.
So in the rest of this course,
we'll explore different ways in which we
can improve upon the imperative view of
reactive programming that's
embodied in the observer pattern.
In this week we are going to look at
Functional Reactive Programming as
an alternative to treat the whole,
these event sequences in a functional way.
In the next two weeks we
will look at related but
different ways of abstracting our events
and event streams with futures and
observables and in the last three weeks
of this course we will tackle concurrency
head on we will express concurrency and
handle it using Actors.