So in this session we are going
to look at a different take of
event handling programs, a functional
view of events that's embodied in
functional reactive programming.
You've seen that reactive programming is
all about reacting to some sequences of
events that happen in time.
The functional view is that we can
actually take such a sequence of events
and aggregate it into a signal.
So, a signal is a value
that changes over time, and
it's represented as a function from
the time domain to the value domain.
That means that instead of propagating
updates to mutable state one by one,
we define new signals in
terms of existing ones.
In a single operation,
we can define a new signal in terms of
signals that we have already defined.
So let's make this
concretely as an example.
Let's say we want to
track mouse positions or
here we'll substitute
the mouse with my pen.
An user moves the mouse,
usually a sequence of events is fired.
Each time the mouse is at a new position,
the application gets a mouse moved event
with the current position of the mouse.
And it would have to handle that event
by updating its internal state and
all these updates would
typically be imperative.
How can I list this into
a functional view point?
So, the core idea is
that I define a signal,
call it also mousePosition,
which is now a signal of position,
which at any point in time represents
the current mouse position.
So, it's a function from the domain
of time values to this curve.
At the initial time value the position
was here, and then it would go
progressively until the fin, at the final
time value the position was here.
That gives me a function from
time values to positions.
Functional Reactive Programming
started in 1997 with the paper
Functional Reactive Animation by
Conal Elliot and Paul Hudak, and
Conal also wrote a,
a language called Fran,
which was implemented as
an embedded library in Haskell.
There have been quite a few FRP systems
since, both standalone languages and
embedded libraries.
The list is too long to give you a,
a complete picture, so
I just give you some examples.
Flapjax is one.
Elm, Bacon.js both target JavaScript.
React4J is a Java library that does
a minimal reactive programming framework.
Related but
not quite the same are the event streaming
data flow programming systems such as Rx.
In fact we will see Rx more in two weeks.
They're related to FRP but
commonly the FRP in the strict
sense is not used for this.
We will introduce FRP not with one of
the existing frameworks but with a really
minimal class, which we will define
ourselves, which we call frp.signal, and
we'll explain the implementation of
frp.signal at the end of the next module.
frp.signal is modeled after the library
Scala.react, which is described
in the paper Deprecating the Observer
Pattern by Ingo Maier and myself.
And in fact the React4J librariy's also
influenced by the Scala.react library so
it has abstractions that are a bit
similar to what we are going to see here.
So let's have a closer look at signals.
There are two fundamental
operations over signal.
First, I can obtain the value
of a signal at the current time.
In our frp.signal library
that's expressed by appli,
applying the signal to
an empty parameter list.
So mousePosition open parenths closed
parenths would give us the mouse position
at the current time.
The second fundamental operation is to
define a signal in terms of other signals.
In our library that's expressed
by the signal constructor.
So let's do an example.
Let's say I have drawn my curve.
And I have given the rectangle like this.
And I want to define a new
signal which is either true or
false depending on whether the curve of
the mouse was in the rectangle or not.
So that new signal would
look something this,
would start with false and at this
point in time it would jump to true and
it would stay true for a while and
it would go back to false.
So that's false.
That's true.
So it's a discrete signal with two states.
Here's how I would define it.
I would define the signal inRectangle
which takes its parameters the coordinates
of the rectangle given as a lower left
corner and an upper right corner.
As it's defined by this expression here.
So what that says is that at each
point in time I return the signal
that looks at the mouse position at the
same point in time, at the current point
in time, and returns whether that
position is between the lower left, and
the upper right corners.
So, we've seen the signal syntax to define
the rectangle signal in terms of the mouse
position signal.
But it can also be used to define
a signal that has no dependencies and
always defines the same value.
So, for instance, Signal(3) would define
the signal that was constant three,
that was always the number three.
So we've constant signals, but how do we
define the signal that varies in time.
Well, we've seen already some of these
varying signals are defined externally,
something like mousePosition
that the system could give us.
We could also map over the external
defined signals that vary in time and
that gives us new signals
that vary in time.
Or the other way is that we can use a var.
A var is a subclass of signal
that we are going to see next.
So far,
all values of type signal are immutable.
A signal is an immutable function
from time to the signal values.
But in fact our library also defines
a subclass Var of Signals for
signals that can be changed.
The change is done by means of an update
operation, which Var provides.
And that updater operation
allows to redefine the value
of a Var signal from the current time on.
So if we look at this example here,
we define sig to be a Var 3,
so that's a signal that, for
now, is always the constant 3,
until the point where I define
an update operation on that signal.
From that point on,
it will always be 5, until, of course,
there's a next update operation,
maybe happening in the future.
So, the update operation uses the name
update for a reason because in fact in
Scala update calls can be rewritten as
assignments using some syntactic sugar.
You've probably known,
seen it already when working with arrays.
For array arr,
you would write arr(i) equals 0.
And what actually happens
here is that this expression,
that this assignment is
translated to arr.update(i, 0).
And that would call the update method
in class Array which has
this definition here.
So, update takes an index and the value
of the element type of the array and
returns unit.
So, under the covers,
when you write an index assignment like
that you really can't call to update.
Generally, an indexed assignment
like f of E1 to En equals E
is translated by the scala
compiler to f.update E1, En, E.
And that works not just for
arrays, but for
all types that define an update
method of the right error pin.
And that also works if n equals 0.
So if there are no indices, that means
that we call f open parenthesis,
close parens equals E is a shorthand for
f.update(E).
So since we have such an update method
on signal, it means that sig.update 5,
a call like that can be abbreviated
to simply sig () equals 5.
You probably notice that signals of type
Var look a bit like mutable variables,
where sig() is dereferencing,
reading the variable.
And sig() equals new|Value is
writing the variable corrupted.
But there's a crucial difference
we can map over signals,
which gives us a relation between two
signals that's maintained automatically,
at all future points in time.
Whereas for variables,
no such mechanisms exists.
You have to update all variables manually
whenever some dependent variable changes.
So, for instance, if we have a variable a,
initialized to 2 and
then b would be 2 times a.
And then we would update
a equals a plus 1.
And the value of b does not automatically
get updated together with the value of a.
So, b would still be four even after that
assignment, we'd have to up update it
manually to say while b is now again
two times a, so that would give it six.
Where as if we take the same thing with
signals, it would looks like this.
So we would have a signal which is
assumed to be a var signal, constant two.
The signal b,
it's assumed to be 2 times a and that,
assignment would establish already
essentially the relationship between b and
a forever in the future.
So if now a is defined to be 3 then,
the signal b would be
automatically updated to 6.
We're going to repeat now the BankAccount
example we've seen in the last section
with signals.
We'll add a signal called balance to
BankAccounts and we will define a function
consolidated which produces the sum of
all balances of a given list of accounts.
So I have on screen my
class BankAccount from
essentially the original example
without any event rendering.
Deposit and withdraw method and
this variable balance.
How do we make this into
a source of an FRP signal?
Well, one approach would be to say
well let's make balance a signal.
So, it would be a val, and
that would be a Var of 0,
so our balance is still a variable,
but now it's a signal.
So now, we say, well if the deposit
method would update that signal,
let's just write it like this for now.
And the amount method
would test that signal,
sorry, and the withdraw method would test
the signal and again, update it like this.
So, that's how a straw man for a bank
account with signals, that was easy.
Right?
We just change the Var balance into
a variable signal and
brought everything over.
So let's test that with a worksheet.
I have written a worksheet accounts and
have given already the header of function
consolidated which should return the sum
of all the balances of the accounts and
just lists here, so.
So, the type of the consolidated
would be then the signal event and
it's the finished end would
be to define a signal and
the signal is defined by means of
mapping over all our accounts for
each one we would take the balance.
And we take the sum of the whole thing.
And of course, we have to take
the balance at the current time.
So it'll be written like this.
So that gives us
the function consolidated.
What we do now is we define,
as before, a number
of bank accounts.
[SOUND] Then we want to find out
the total balance in consolidated so
the value of consolidated
at the current time.
All right, so we get zero as expected.
Let's deposit some amount in A and
try again.
Oops, we got an insertion error.
So what does it read here, it says cyclic.
Let me just bring that up.
Cyclic definition, cyclic signal
definition, that's what it says.
So, what have we done wrong?
So, it must be in the bank account.
Let's bring that bank account up again.
So in fact the arrow
appeared at this line here.
And if you look at this line then you
must conclude that indeed it does,
makes no sense whatsoever.
What we've done here is to say, well, the
signal balance which is a function over
time, is the same as itself plus amount,
where amount is greater than 0.
So, obviously an equation
like that has no solution.
You can't define a function
that at each point in time,
is the value of the function
itself plus amount.
So, that didn't work.
And, in fact,
the system has called us out by
throwing an insertion which says
there was a cyclic signal definition.
We have defined balance
in terms of itself.
So how do we fix it?
Well, what we need to fix, what we need
to do to fix it, is we have to pull out
the balance signal into
a separate definition here that
pulls out the current value of balance and
then just does this thing here.
And we do the same thing here, so.
Val b equals balance and
balance equals b plus amount.
So how is that different?
Well, what we do now is to say we
take the current value of balance,
call it b, and then define the new balance
after that to be that value plus amount.
So what we did,
do now is not define a cyclic definition,
not to have a cyclic definition, but
indeed define a constant function which
will return at all points in the future,
the value of this expression here.
So you see that
the interaction of state and
functions is very subtle as we have
observed at several points before.
It makes an obvious difference but
the balance here is defined as the right
hand side of a signal definition.
Or pulled out into its own [INAUDIBLE].
Let's redo the worksheet
with that example.
And in fact, now we get,
the correct result, the a deposit as 20.
Let's deposit as before 30 in, b.
Call it again.
And that would give, give us this here.
Let's go a little bit further and
say we want to have another signal,
which defines an exchange rate.
Let's call
Let's say the exchange rate is first 246,
let's say, dollars for Bitcoins.
And let's say our value, our total sum is
inDollars is then what we had before,
a signal that takes c times
the signal xchange rate.
And now we would have a different Signal
inDollar which has this value here.
Now if we changed, let's say,
b again, b withdraw 10,
and look at the result inDollar.
Then you, then you see that the deduction
in b is reflected in our inDollar results.
So at the first the signal c got updated,
and
then the signal inDollar got updated,
as well.
So that was the bank account example
redone with signals instead of
subscribers.
If you compared the two solutions then
you will notice that the solution with
signals is much shorter.
And you could also argue much cleaner
because there is much less state updates
than in the observer solution,
which is inherently imperative.
We've also seen in the example that
there's an important difference
between variable assignments
such as this one here, and
a signal update,
such that the one that you see here.
In, in the first case that,
in that variable assignment,
the new value of v is
the old value of v plus 1.
So implicitly, there is a notion of
old value vers, versus new values.
When you update a signal,
there's no such notion.
So what you are trying to say here is
that in fact, in fact that the signal s
is the same as the signal s plus 1,
which obviously makes no sense.
So here's an exercise for you.
Consider those two code fragments.
The first one says num equals Var(1).
And we have a signal that is num times 2,
and then we update num to be 2.
And the second one is quite similar, so
we start with a var num equals Var(1).
The signal twice is as before.
But finally,
we define num to be equal Var(2).
Are those two code fragments equivalent?
That means do, would they yield
the same final value for twice?
So if I evaluate twice here and
I evaluate twice here,
would I get the same value, yes or no?
So let's visualize how these
two code fragments behave.
In the first case, I have the num signal,
which is constant 1.
And the twice signal, which is constant 2.
Then at some point, I change num to 2 and
twice will consequently jump to 4.
So that's the update of
the first code fragment.
Let's have a look at the second one.
So again, I have num equals Var(1).
And twice is 2.
But what I do now is I
define a new signal,
num, and assign it to the variable.
So after this point here, num in fact is,
points to a new signal
that is has the value 2.
Whereas the twice signal, in fact,
would still depend on this signal here
that I have created up here,
so it would stay 2 forever.
So while I have here 2 as the final value,
in the first code, my fragment, it was 4.
And the two fragments
are indeed different.
It just shows a little bit the subtlety
that you have with signal
update versus variables.
It gives you another aspect
of that same difference.