In the last section,
we have seen how to use a very simple
API of signal-send wires for
functional reactive programming.
In this unit, we are going to
take a look under the covers and
see how that simple API
could be implemented.
We're going to develop step by step
a simple implementation of Signals and
Vars whic, as you have seen from
the basis of our approach to frp.
We the two classes of Signal and
Var are assumed to be in a package frp.
We will start with summarizing the APIs as
we have seen them in the module last week.
So here's the API of class signal.
Signal takes as an argument T expression
that constitutes the signal and
it exposes a method apply which gives
you the current value of the signal for
the moment we have left
out its implementation.
There's also an object signal which has
its own apply method, you'll recall that
if object has an apply method then
they enable a syntax like this.
That we can write signal and
then some expression like that and
that would be the form that maps all
the signals or creates constant signals.
So apply takes a binding parameter
expression which is this expression
here that can be evaluated at
multiple points in the future.
And it simply creates a signal
with that expression.
So we've also used Vars so
a Var is a subclass of signal
and it adds one more method and
that's the update method which takes the
expression to be evaluated from now on.
This is our type is unit and
we have again left out the implementation.
Like signals var have an apply method
which allows us to create new vars with
the same syntax as for signals like that.
So now that we have the APIs,
let's see how we could implement them.
Here's the central implementation idea,
each signal maintains three data attempts.
The first one is the current
value of the signal.
The second one is the expression defining
the signal at the present time so
that will be used if you have
to re-evaluate the signal.
And the third one is a set of observers.
The observers are all
the other signals would
depend on the value of the current signal.
The idea then is if the signal
changes be it because its updated or
it depends on another signal that changes,
so
if the signal changes then all
the observers will be re-evaluated.
So that brings us to the question
of dependency maintenance.
How do we record
dependencies in observers?
When we evaluate
a signal-valued expression,
we need to know which signal caller gets
defined or updated by the expression.
If we know that then we can add that
caller to the observers of the signal when
the signal is evaluated, that means when
we take the current value of the signal.
If we have added the caller to the
observer set then we can re-evaluated it
each time the signal's value changes.
So each time a signal's value changes,
all previously observing signals
are re-evaluated and what we also do then,
we clear the set of sig.observers.
Because when we re-evaluate an observer,
if the observer still depends on
the value of the current signal then
it will automatically be
re-entered into the observer set.
But of course it might not depend on
the current signal anymore because maybe
another signal has changed which
is a boolean condition which
makes the execution of the signal go
into a different branch than before.
So that's the central idea,
there's the tricky issue,
how do we find out on whose behalf
a signal expression is evaluated?
So when you, we evaluate the signal
expression, how do we know which other
signal is currently updated or
defined with a signal constructor?
We will first look at one
very simple way to do this,
you might say simplistic way to do this.
And that is to maintain a global
data structure that refers simply to
the current caller and that we will
update as we evaluate signals.
We'll just come back to that later and
discuss the wisdom of doing this and
possible alternatives.
The caller data structure is in
fact accessed in a stack-like
fashion because one evaluation of
a signal might trigger the update or
redefinition of other signals.
So, the way we express this
is in defining a class for
stackable variables that
can be accessed like this.
So here, we would have a global variable,
a value caller which is a stackable
variable with some initial signal.
And then we could update the color in a
scoped fashion by saying color with value.
Some other signal and then some expression
that while the expression evaluates
the color would the value other signal.
And we could get the value out of the
color simply with the syntax color.value.
So those are the use cases,
here's the implementation.
It's rather simple, so the cast stackable
variable has a type around of T and
of valid parameter which
gives it's initial value.
It here's the stack maintained
as a list of values the current
value is the head of the list and
this value operation takes a new value.
And then operation to the perform that
would have this new value as the top this
stack, so what it does is it puts
the new value on the top of the list.
It executes the operation and
when it's done with that it
pops the value of the list, so
the list becomes it own tail.
So let's look at the setup
in object signal,
you see here that in addition to the apply
method the object signal has now
a value caller which is
a stackable variable.
The type parameter of the stackable
variable is of type signal
with an underscore as a parameter.
That means that stackable variables
can take signals of any value type.
Let's have a look at the initial value,
what should that be?
Well initially there is no caller so
we have to express that somehow and
we choose to express it with a so called
sentinel object that we call NoSignal.
So NoSignal is a special signal,
it doesn't have a value at all so
it extends Signal[Nothing].
And it doesn't have
an implementation either so
we can pass the triple question marks
which essentially just mean unimplemented
as the expression value for
unknown signal.
So now that we have done with the setup
let's have a look at the signal class.
As we have mentioned before the signal
class has three items in its state.
They are represented by
three private variables.
The first one is the current expression
which is called here my expression.
Second is the current value of
the signal which is called my value.
And the third is the set of observers,
the initial values of my expression and
my value are both uninitialized.
The initial value of the set
of observers is the empty set.
So how do we initialize myExpr and
myValue?
Well that will be done in
the initial call to the update
function that we are going to see next.
So the update method gets called during
the initialization of the signal and
whenever somebody assigns
a new value to the signal.
It takes the expression to
evaluate the new signal,
assigns it to my expression and
computes the current value of the signal.
So we have to look at compute value next,
here it is.
For now, we use a simplified
version of compute value.
There will be more to add later
where compute value simply evaluates
the current expression with
the current signal as the color and
assigns the result into my value.
So the last part of the signal
class is the apply method,
here is it's implementation.
Apply simply returns the current
value of the signal but
before it does that it adds the current
caller to the set of observers.
And the third part of apply is
an assertion which says that we should
avoid defining cyclic signals
that depend on themselves.
So, as we have seen in an example here,
a signal like this is an error.
[SOUND] So that error condition
gets caught by this assert
which says that the observers of a signal
may not contain the signal itself.
So here, evaluating this expression here
would be done with the current caller s.
So that would mean that s gets added into
the observers of the signal s itself.
So this as assert would be triggered and
you would detect a cyclic,
a signal definition.
If the assert wasn't there the error
would still be detected but
it would be a stack overflow error,
you would get an infinite recursion which
is much less informative than the subset.
So, if you've followed so
far then you should notice that
there's one bit of the implementation
of class signals still missing.
Which is it?
Is it error handling?
Or reevaluating the callers?
Or constructing the observers set?
Well in fact, the missing piece
is reevaluating the callers.
Let's have a look at that next.
So, we've seen that a signal's
current value can change when
somebody calls an update
operation on the Var or
the value of a signal that
the signal depends on changes.
And in the second case,
we need to detect these changes and
propagate them to the observing signal.
The propagation will be
done in compute value so
we will now refine the implementation of
that method, that's what it was before.
You simply evaluate my expression
with the current caller and
assign the result to my value.
And that's a new implementation of com,
compute value, this part is as before but
now we stole the result of evaluating
my expression in a new value, newValue.
And if that new value is
different from the current value
then we perform
the following actions here.
We assign the newValue to myValue,
that's the same as before but
we also take the observers into a local
value obs, clear the set of observers.
And for each element of ops,
we do a compute value.
That will then in turn,
by re-evaluating the signal we
add the observer into the observer set.
So, because that will happen down here,
we should clear the observer set before.
So that was the core of it there
are some little bits still to be done.
One concerns NoSignal in NoSignal,
we have seen that NoSignal doesn't
really have an expression associated with
it so we can't really compute its value.
Because if we would try to evaluate
the type of question mark we would
get an unimplemented exception.
So we overwrite compute value and
no signal to be the empty expression
that returns unit directly.
So a second bit of functionality
still missing concerns Vars.
We call that a Var is a Signal that
can be updated by the client program.
And in fact, all the functionality we
need for that is already present in class
Signal because in fact signal does
have already an update method.
Here you see the update method essentially
does the right thing, it assigns
the expression to be the current
expression and it recomputes the value.
But it is protected in class signal which
means only subclasses can get at it.
Whereas clients of signal cannot which
of course is intended because we
want to make signal immutable clients of
signal should not be able to call update.
But of course clients of var should be
able to call updates, so the way we
achieve this is that we override
the update method, make it public in var.
And the implementation of that update
would simply be a call to the super class,
super.update(expr).
So that way essentially,
we reuse the same implementation but
we now expose it publicly.
So this is it, I would argue that
our implementation of functional
reactive programming is quite
stunning in its simplicity.
But you might object that it's
a little bit too simplistic.
In particular, you might say well,
this makes use of the worse kind
of state named the global state.
Indeed in the object signal
which is a global object,
we have this value caller which
is a StackableVariable and
that's caller is accessed by all the code
in an application using signals.
One particular problem here is,
what happens if we try to evaluate sev,
several signal expressions in parallel?
Then multiple threads could access
caller at the same time and
could also update caller and
stackable variable.
So without protection in
terms of synchronization or
something we would get raised
conditions and unpredictable results.
So one way to get around the problem of
concurrent accesses to global state such
as collier is to use synchronization.
But synchronization has its own set of
problems because it blocks threads,
so bleds, threads might wait
indefinitely long it can be slow and
it can lead to deadlocks.
Another solution that is
more appropriate here
is to replace global state
by Thread-Local State.
So thread-local state means that
each thread in an application
accesses its own copy of the variable.
So the variable is global for the thread
but it's not shared between threads.
Thread-local state is supported in Java
through Java neutral thread-local and
that's wrapped in Scala through
class scala.util.DynamicVariable.
And we have engineered
that in fact the API of
StackableVariable matches exactly
the API of DynamicVariable.
So we can simply swap out
StackableVariable, the global state
that we want to avoid for DynamicVariable
which gives us the thread-local state.
So the signal now would read
caller equals new DynamicVariable
with the same type parameter and
initial value.
So, replacing stackable variable with
dynamic variable's a definite improvement
because we avoid the raised conditions
that the global variable would entail.
Otherwise, if you have
a multithreaded application but
it comes with a number
of other disadvantages.
Well the first one is actually shared
with the global state and that's,
that essentially the state is imperative.
We have imperative state that's indirectly
accessed by the whole application.
So this gives essentially a high
degree of entanglement of
dependencies that are not
made explicit in the types or
input output results of functions and
that are, therefore, problematic.
So that's essentially,
the problem of all imperative state but
the more global that state is,
the worse the problem.
The second shortcoming of
thread-local state is,
is that it's not terribly efficient
because every access to its thread-local
variable in fact involves
a global hash table lookup.
So the JDK stores essentially
all thread-local variables
in a hash table that's associated
with the current thread.
And accessing that hash table is
not as fast as if you just
select that variable directly.
And the third possible
disadvantage is that if
you have situations where you don't have
a straightforward multi-threaded solution.
But where you, let's say, you multiplex
frets over executors or tasks so
your threads have become worker's
threads and thread-local doesn't work so
well because one task might run for
a while in one thread.
And then it might switch
to a different thread and
I would like to take thread-local variable
with it but of course the thread-local
variable gets locked to the current state
so in that case it wouldn't be a solution.
So to summarize, thread-local state is an
improvement of unprotected global state.
But it has its own set of problems,
it's fragile plays well only with
some approaches to concurrency.
And it has still the problem
that it is fundamentally
state that is shared by a large
part of the application.
There's actually another possible solution
which is much cleaner and that is to
simply pass down the current caller into
all the signal evaluated expressions.
Now if you do that explicitly it would
produce a lot of overhead essentially
every signal of every expression
has to have another parameter.
And these parameters have to be
threaded through everything.
But if you make the parameter
impressive then
a lot of that burden can
actually be avoided.
So the idea is that instead of
maintaining a thread-local variable,
we pass its current value into a signal
expression as an implicit parameter.
And it's purely functional but
it currently requires
still some more boilerplate
than the thread-local solution.
Because essential
expressions have to close,
have to take this implicit
value as a parameter.
Future versions of Scala might
actually solve that problem so
we're going to be tinkering with some
ideas of how that could be streamlined.
So to conclude, we've given a quick
tour of functional reactive
programing with some user examples and
full implementation.
This is just a taste though there's
much more to be discovered.
In particular, we've only covered one
particular style of functional reactive
programming the style that treats discrete
signals that are changed by events.
There are other variants of functional
reactive programming that treat
continuous signals sometimes just
continuous, and sometimes continuous,
and just quick together.
So a continuous sequence
signal can not be broken up
in to a sequence of events because it's
changes its value at each time interval.
What we do instead typically in
touch systems is use sampling
instead of event propocation.
So that means we have signals that are
continues over the real time values but
what we'd need to do is not compute
the signal at each possible point in time.
But we can actually sample it at
as needed by the application with
sufficient density.
So, fascinating subjects for
further exploration.
What we will do in the next week and
the week after is take
a slightly different tact.
Eric Myer will take over and
tell you about futures and observables.
Observables are another
form of event stream
that is related to functional reactive
programming but it can asynchronous and
it can be non-deterministic.